The|I-MISC Oxford|I-MISC Companion|I-MISC to|I-MISC Philosophy|I-MISC says|O ,|O "|O there|O is|O no|O single|O defining|O position|O that|O all|O anarchists|O hold|O ,|O and|O those|O considered|O anarchists|O at|O best|O share|O a|O certain|O family|O resemblance|O .|O "|O
In|O the|O end|O ,|O for|O anarchist|O historian|O Daniel|I-PER Guerin|I-PER "|O Some|O anarchists|O are|O more|O individualistic|O than|O social|O ,|O some|O more|O social|O than|O individualistic|O .|O
From|O this|O climate|O William|I-PER Godwin|I-PER developed|O what|O many|O consider|O the|O first|O expression|O of|O modern|O anarchist|O thought|O .|O
Godwin|I-PER was|O ,|O according|O to|O Peter|I-PER Kropotkin|I-PER ,|O "|O the|O first|O to|O formulate|O the|O political|O and|O economical|O conceptions|O of|O anarchism|O ,|O even|O though|O he|O did|O not|O give|O that|O name|O to|O the|O ideas|O developed|O in|O his|O work|O "|O ,|O while|O Godwin|I-PER attached|O his|O anarchist|O ideas|O to|O an|O early|O Edmund|I-PER Burke|I-PER .|O
The|O first|O to|O describe|O himself|O as|O an|O anarchist|O was|O Pierre-Joseph|I-PER Proudhon|I-PER ,|O a|O French|I-MISC philosopher|O and|O politician|O ,|O which|O led|O some|O to|O call|O him|O the|O founder|O of|O modern|O anarchist|O theory|O .|O
Its|O classical|O period|O ,|O which|O scholars|O demarcate|O as|O from|O 1860|O to|O 1939|O ,|O is|O associated|O with|O the|O working-class|O movements|O of|O the|O nineteenth|O century|O and|O the|O Spanish|I-MISC Civil|I-MISC War-era|I-MISC struggles|O against|O fascism|O .|O
Due|O to|O its|O links|O to|O active|O workers|O '|O movements|O ,|O the|I-MISC International|I-MISC became|O a|O significant|O organization|O .|O
Karl|I-PER Marx|I-PER became|O a|O leading|O figure|O in|O the|I-MISC International|I-MISC and|O a|O member|O of|O its|O General|I-ORG Council|I-ORG .|O
Proudhon|I-PER 's|O followers|O ,|O the|O mutualists|O ,|O opposed|O Marx|I-PER 's|O state|O socialism|O ,|O advocating|O political|O abstentionism|O and|O small|O property|O holdings|O .|O
They|O allied|O themselves|O with|O the|O federalist|O socialist|O sections|O of|O the|I-MISC International|I-MISC ,|O who|O advocated|O the|O revolutionary|O overthrow|O of|O the|O state|O and|O the|O collectivization|O of|O property|O .|O
Subsequently|O ,|O the|I-MISC International|I-MISC became|O polarised|O into|O two|O camps|O ,|O with|O Marx|I-PER and|O Bakunin|I-PER as|O their|O respective|O figureheads|O .|O
In|O 1872|O ,|O the|O conflict|O climaxed|O with|O a|O final|O split|O between|O the|O two|O groups|O at|O the|O Hague|I-MISC Congress|I-MISC ,|O where|O Bakunin|I-PER and|O James|I-PER Guillaume|I-PER were|O expelled|O from|O the|I-MISC International|I-MISC and|O its|O headquarters|O were|O transferred|O to|O New|I-LOC York|I-LOC .|O
In|O response|O ,|O the|O federalist|O sections|O formed|O their|O own|O International|I-ORG at|O the|O St.|I-ORG Imier|I-ORG Congress|I-ORG ,|O adopting|O a|O revolutionary|O anarchist|O program|O .|O
In|O response|O ,|O unions|O across|O America|I-LOC prepared|O a|O general|O strike|O in|O support|O of|O the|O event|O .|O
The|O incident|O became|O known|O as|O the|O Haymarket|I-PER affair|I-PER ,|O and|O was|O a|O setback|O for|O the|O labour|O movement|O and|O the|O struggle|O for|O the|O eight|O hour|O day|O .|O
The|O event|O also|O had|O the|O secondary|O purpose|O of|O memorializing|O workers|O killed|O as|O a|O result|O of|O the|O Haymarket|I-PER affair|I-PER .|O
Malatesta|I-PER warned|O that|O the|O syndicalists|O aims|O were|O in|O perpetuating|O syndicalism|O itself|O ,|O whereas|O anarchists|O must|O always|O have|O anarchy|O as|O their|O end|O and|O consequently|O refrain|O from|O committing|O to|O any|O particular|O method|O of|O achieving|O it|O .|O
The|O most|O successful|O was|O the|O Confederación|I-ORG Nacional|I-ORG del|I-ORG Trabajo|I-ORG (|O National|I-ORG Confederation|I-ORG of|I-ORG Labour|I-ORG :|O CNT|I-ORG )|O ,|O founded|O in|O 1910|O .|O
Before|O the|O 1940s|O ,|O the|O CNT|I-ORG was|O the|O major|O force|O in|O Spanish|I-MISC working|O class|O politics|O ,|O attracting|O 1.58|O million|O members|O at|O one|O point|O and|O playing|O a|O major|O role|O in|O the|O Spanish|I-MISC Civil|I-MISC War|I-MISC .|O
CGT|I-ORG membership|O was|O estimated|O to|O be|O around|O 100,000|O for|O the|O year|O 2003|O .|O
Other|O active|O syndicalist|O movements|O include|O the|O US|I-LOC Workers|I-ORG Solidarity|I-ORG Alliance|I-ORG and|O the|O UK|I-LOC Solidarity|I-ORG Federation|I-ORG .|O
Some|O anarchists|O ,|O such|O as|O Johann|I-PER Most|I-PER ,|O advocated|O publicizing|O violent|O acts|O of|O retaliation|O against|O counter-revolutionaries|O because|O "|O we|O preach|O not|O only|O action|O in|O and|O for|O itself|O ,|O but|O also|O action|O as|O propaganda|O .|O "|O
The|O anarcho-syndicalist|O ,|O Fernand|I-PER Pelloutier|I-PER ,|O argued|O in|O 1895|O for|O renewed|O anarchist|O involvement|O in|O the|O labor|O movement|O on|O the|O basis|O that|O anarchism|O could|O do|O very|O well|O without|O "|O the|O individual|O dynamiter|O .|O "|O
State|O repression|O (|O including|O the|O infamous|O 1894|O French|I-MISC lois|O scélérates|O )|O of|O the|O anarchist|O and|O labor|O movements|O following|O the|O few|O successful|O bombings|O and|O assassinations|O may|O have|O contributed|O to|O the|O abandonment|O of|O these|O kinds|O of|O tactics|O ,|O although|O reciprocally|O state|O repression|O ,|O in|O the|O first|O place|O ,|O may|O have|O played|O a|O role|O in|O these|O isolated|O acts|O .|O
For|O example|O ,|O U.S.|I-LOC President|O McKinley|I-PER 's|O assassin|O Leon|I-PER Czolgosz|I-PER claimed|O to|O have|O been|O influenced|O by|O anarchist|O and|O feminist|O Emma|I-PER Goldman|I-PER .|O
This|O was|O in|O spite|O of|O Goldman|I-PER 's|O disavowal|O of|O any|O association|O with|O him|O ,|O his|O registered|O membership|O in|O the|O Republican|I-ORG Party|I-ORG ,|O and|O never|O having|O belonged|O to|O an|O anarchist|O organization|O .|O
Propaganda|O of|O the|O deed|O was|O abandoned|O by|O the|O vast|O majority|O of|O the|O anarchist|O movement|O after|O World|I-MISC War|I-MISC I|I-MISC (|O 1914|O --|O 18|O )|O and|O the|O 1917|I-MISC October|I-MISC Revolution|I-MISC .|O
Important|O factors|O towards|O this|O include|O state|O repression|O ,|O the|O level|O of|O organization|O of|O the|O labour|O movement|O ,|O and|O the|O influence|O of|O the|O October|I-MISC Revolution|I-MISC [|O citation|O needed|O ]|O .|O
Anarchists|O participated|O alongside|O the|O Bolsheviks|I-ORG in|O both|O February|O and|O October|I-MISC revolutions|I-MISC ,|O and|O were|O initially|O enthusiastic|O about|O the|O Bolshevik|I-ORG coup|O .|O
However|O ,|O the|O Bolsheviks|I-ORG soon|O turned|O against|O the|O anarchists|O and|O other|O left-wing|O opposition|O ,|O a|O conflict|O that|O culminated|O in|O the|O 1921|O Kronstadt|I-MISC rebellion|I-MISC which|O the|O new|O government|O repressed|O .|O
Both|O wrote|O accounts|O of|O their|O experiences|O in|O Russia|I-LOC ,|O criticizing|O the|O amount|O of|O control|O the|O Bolsheviks|I-ORG exercised|O .|O
The|O victory|O of|O the|O Bolsheviks|I-ORG in|O the|O October|I-MISC Revolution|I-MISC and|O the|O resulting|O Russian|I-MISC Civil|I-MISC War|I-MISC did|O serious|O damage|O to|O anarchist|O movements|O internationally|O .|O
Platformist|I-MISC groups|O active|O today|O include|O the|O Workers|I-ORG Solidarity|I-ORG Movement|I-ORG in|O Ireland|I-ORG and|O the|O North|I-ORG Eastern|I-ORG Federation|I-ORG of|I-ORG Anarchist|I-ORG Communists|I-ORG of|O North|I-LOC America|I-LOC .|O
Italy|I-ORG saw|O the|O first|O struggles|O between|O anarchists|O and|O fascists|O .|O
Italian|I-ORG anarchists|I-ORG played|O a|O key|O role|O in|O the|O anti-fascist|O organisation|O Arditi|I-MISC del|I-MISC Popolo|I-MISC ,|O which|O was|O strongest|O in|O areas|O with|O anarchist|O traditions|O ,|O and|O achieved|O some|O success|O in|O their|O activism|O ,|O such|O as|O repelling|O Blackshirts|I-ORG in|O the|O anarchist|O stronghold|O of|O Parma|I-LOC in|O August|O 1922|O .|O
But|O in|O 1936|O ,|O the|O CNT|I-ORG changed|O its|O policy|O and|O anarchist|O votes|O helped|O bring|O the|O popular|O front|O back|O to|O power|O .|O
Months|O later|O ,|O the|O former|O ruling|O class|O responded|O with|O an|O attempted|O coup|O causing|O the|O Spanish|I-MISC Civil|I-MISC War|I-MISC (|O 1936|O --|O 1939|O )|O .|O
Stalinist-led|O troops|O suppressed|O the|O collectives|O and|O persecuted|O both|O dissident|I-ORG Marxists|I-ORG and|O anarchists|O .|O
In|O the|O U.K.|I-LOC this|O was|O associated|O with|O the|O punk|O rock|O movement|O ,|O as|O exemplified|O by|O bands|O such|O as|O Crass|I-ORG and|O the|O Sex|I-ORG Pistols|I-ORG .|O
The|O American|I-ORG Civil|I-ORG Rights|I-ORG Movement|I-ORG and|O the|O movement|O against|O the|O war|I-MISC in|I-MISC Vietnam|I-MISC also|O contributed|O to|O the|O revival|O of|O North|I-MISC American|I-MISC anarchism|O .|O
Anarchist|O anthropologist|O David|I-PER Graeber|I-PER and|O anarchist|O historian|O Andrej|I-PER Grubacic|I-PER have|O posited|O a|O rupture|O between|O generations|O of|O anarchism|O ,|O with|O those|O "|O who|O often|O still|O have|O not|O shaken|O the|O sectarian|O habits|O "|O of|O the|O nineteenth|O century|O contrasted|O with|O the|O younger|O activists|O who|O are|O "|O much|O more|O informed|O ,|O among|O other|O elements|O ,|O by|O indigenous|O ,|O feminist|O ,|O ecological|O and|O cultural-critical|O ideas|O "|O ,|O and|O who|O by|O the|O turn|O of|O the|O 21st|O century|O formed|O "|O by|O far|O the|O majority|O "|O of|O anarchists|O .|O
Anarchists|O became|O known|O for|O their|O involvement|O in|O protests|O against|O the|O meetings|O of|O the|O World|I-ORG Trade|I-ORG Organization|I-ORG (|O WTO|I-ORG )|O ,|O Group|I-ORG of|I-ORG Eight|I-ORG ,|O and|O the|O World|I-ORG Economic|I-ORG Forum|I-ORG .|O
A|O landmark|O struggle|O of|O this|O period|O was|O the|O confrontations|O at|O WTO|I-ORG conference|I-ORG in|I-ORG Seattle|I-ORG in|I-ORG 1999|I-ORG .|O
International|I-ORG anarchist|O federations|O in|O existence|O include|O the|O International|I-ORG of|I-ORG Anarchist|I-ORG Federations|I-ORG ,|O the|O International|I-ORG Workers|I-ORG '|I-ORG Association|I-ORG ,|O and|O International|I-ORG Libertarian|I-ORG Solidarity|I-ORG .|O
One|O reaction|O against|O sectarianism|O within|O the|O anarchist|O milieu|O was|O "|O anarchism|O without|O adjectives|O "|O ,|O a|O call|O for|O toleration|O first|O adopted|O by|O Fernando|I-PER Tarrida|I-PER del|I-PER Mármol|I-PER in|O 1889|O in|O response|O to|O the|O "|O bitter|O debates|O "|O of|O anarchist|O theory|O at|O the|O time|O .|O
Proudhon|I-PER proposed|O spontaneous|O order|O ,|O whereby|O organization|O emerges|O without|O central|O authority|O ,|O a|O "|O positive|O anarchy|O "|O where|O order|O arises|O when|O everybody|O does|O "|O what|O he|O wishes|O and|O only|O what|O he|O wishes|O "|O and|O where|O "|O business|O transactions|O alone|O produce|O the|O social|O order|O .|O "|O
According|O to|O William|I-PER Batchelder|I-PER Greene|I-PER ,|O each|O worker|O in|O the|O mutualist|O system|O would|O receive|O "|O just|O and|O exact|O pay|O for|O his|O work|O ;|O services|O equivalent|O in|O cost|O being|O exchangeable|O for|O services|O equivalent|O in|O cost|O ,|O without|O profit|O or|O discount|O .|O "|O
Proudhon|I-PER first|O characterised|O his|O goal|O as|O a|O "|O third|O form|O of|O society|O ,|O the|O synthesis|O of|O communism|O and|O property|O .|O "|O
Godwin|I-PER ,|O a|O philosophical|O anarchist|O ,|O from|O a|O rationalist|O and|O utilitarian|O basis|O opposed|O revolutionary|O action|O and|O saw|O a|O minimal|O state|O as|O a|O present|O "|O necessary|O evil|O "|O that|O would|O become|O increasingly|O irrelevant|O and|O powerless|O by|O the|O gradual|O spread|O of|O knowledge|O .|O
Godwin|I-PER advocated|O extreme|O individualism|O ,|O proposing|O that|O all|O cooperation|O in|O labour|O be|O eliminated|O on|O the|O premise|O that|O this|O would|O be|O most|O conducive|O with|O the|O general|O good|O .|O
Godwin|I-PER was|O a|O utilitarian|O who|O believed|O that|O all|O individuals|O are|O not|O of|O equal|O value|O ,|O with|O some|O of|O us|O "|O of|O more|O worth|O and|O importance|O "|O than|O others|O depending|O on|O our|O utility|O in|O bringing|O about|O social|O good|O .|O
Godwin|I-PER opposed|O government|O because|O he|O saw|O it|O as|O infringing|O on|O the|O individual|O 's|O right|O to|O "|O private|O judgement|O "|O to|O determine|O which|O actions|O most|O maximise|O utility|O ,|O but|O also|O makes|O a|O critique|O of|O all|O authority|O over|O the|O individual|O 's|O judgement|O .|O
This|O aspect|O of|O Godwin|I-PER 's|O philosophy|O ,|O stripped|O of|O utilitarian|O motivations|O ,|O was|O developed|O into|O a|O more|O extreme|O form|O later|O by|O Stirner|I-PER .|O
The|O most|O extreme|O form|O of|O individualist|O anarchism|O ,|O called|O "|O egoism,|O "|O or|O egoist|O anarchism|O ,|O was|O expounded|O by|O one|O of|O the|O earliest|O and|O best-known|O proponents|O of|O individualist|O anarchism|O ,|O Max|I-PER Stirner|I-PER .|O
Stirner|I-PER 's|O The|I-MISC Ego|I-MISC and|I-MISC Its|I-MISC Own|I-MISC ,|O published|O in|O 1844|O ,|O is|O a|O founding|O text|O of|O the|O philosophy|O .|O
To|O Stirner|I-PER ,|O rights|O were|O spooks|O in|O the|O mind|O ,|O and|O he|O held|O that|O society|O does|O not|O exist|O but|O "|O the|O individuals|O are|O its|O reality|O "|O .|O
Stirner|I-PER 's|O philosophy|O has|O been|O seen|O as|O a|O precedent|O of|O existentialism|O with|O other|O thinkers|O like|O Friedrich|I-PER Nietzsche|I-PER and|O Søren|I-PER Kierkegaard|I-PER .|O
Collectivist|O anarchism|O ,|O also|O referred|O to|O as|O "|O revolutionary|O socialism|O "|O or|O a|O form|O of|O such|O ,|O is|O a|O revolutionary|O form|O of|O anarchism|O ,|O commonly|O associated|O with|O Mikhail|I-PER Bakunin|I-PER and|O Johann|I-PER Most|I-PER .|O
It|O was|O inspired|O by|O the|O late|O 19th|O century|O writings|O of|O early|O feminist|O anarchists|O such|O as|O Lucy|I-PER Parsons|I-PER ,|O Emma|I-PER Goldman|I-PER ,|O Voltairine|I-PER de|I-PER Cleyre|I-PER ,|O and|O Dora|I-PER Marsden|I-PER .|O
It|O developed|O "|O mostly|O in|O Holland|I-LOC ,|O Britain|I-LOC ,|O and|O the|O U.S.|I-LOC ,|O before|O and|O during|O the|O Second|I-MISC World|I-MISC War|I-MISC "|O .|O
Another|O recent|O form|O of|O anarchism|O critical|O of|O formal|O anarchist|O movements|O is|O insurrectionary|O anarchism|O ,|O which|O advocates|O informal|O organization|O and|O active|O resistance|O to|O the|O state|O ;|O its|O proponents|O include|O Wolfi|I-PER Landstreicher|I-PER and|O Alfredo|I-PER M.|I-PER Bonanno|I-PER .|O
Free|O love|O advocates|O sometimes|O traced|O their|O roots|O back|O to|O Josiah|I-PER Warren|I-PER and|O to|O experimental|O communities|O ,|O viewed|O sexual|O freedom|O as|O a|O clear|O ,|O direct|O expression|O of|O an|O individual|O 's|O self-ownership|O .|O
In|O New|I-LOC York|I-LOC 's|O Greenwich|I-LOC Village|I-LOC ,|O bohemian|O feminists|O and|O socialists|O advocated|O self-realisation|O and|O pleasure|O for|O women|O (|O and|O also|O men|O )|O in|O the|O here|O and|O now|O .|O
They|O encouraged|O playing|O with|O sexual|O roles|O and|O sexuality|O ,|O and|O the|O openly|O bisexual|O radical|O Edna|I-PER St.|I-PER Vincent|I-PER Millay|I-PER and|O the|O lesbian|O anarchist|O Margaret|I-PER Anderson|I-PER were|O prominent|O among|O them|O .|O
Thus|O it|O came|O about|O that|O she|O was|O the|O first|O and|O only|O woman|O ,|O indeed|O the|O first|O and|O only|O American|I-MISC ,|O to|O take|O up|O the|O defense|O of|O homosexual|O love|O before|O the|O general|O public|O .|O "|O
More|O recently|O ,|O the|O British|I-MISC anarcho-pacifist|O Alex|I-PER Comfort|I-PER gained|O notoriety|O during|O the|O sexual|O revolution|O for|O writing|O the|O bestseller|O sex|O manual|O The|I-MISC Joy|I-MISC of|I-MISC Sex|I-MISC .|O
Max|I-PER Stirner|I-PER wrote|O in|O 1842|O a|O long|O essay|O on|O education|O called|O The|I-MISC False|I-MISC Principle|I-MISC of|I-MISC our|I-MISC Education|I-MISC .|O
In|O it|O Stirner|I-PER names|O his|O educational|O principle|O "|O personalist,|O "|O explaining|O that|O self-understanding|O consists|O in|O hourly|O self-creation|O .|O
Perhaps|O the|O best-known|O effort|O in|O this|O field|O was|O Francisco|I-PER Ferrer|I-PER 's|O Modern|I-ORG School|I-ORG (|O Escuela|I-ORG Moderna|I-ORG )|O ,|O a|O project|O which|O exercised|O a|O considerable|O influence|O on|O Catalan|I-MISC education|O and|O on|O experimental|O techniques|O of|O teaching|O generally|O .|O "|O
The|O first|O of|O these|O was|O started|O in|O New|I-LOC York|I-LOC City|I-LOC in|O 1911|O .|O
Summerhill|I-ORG is|O often|O cited|O as|O an|O example|O of|O anarchism|O in|O practice|O .|O
The|O term|O deschooling|O was|O popularized|O by|O Ivan|I-PER Illich|I-PER ,|O who|O argued|O that|O the|O school|O as|O an|O institution|O is|O dysfunctional|O for|O self-determined|O learning|O and|O serves|O the|O creation|O of|O a|O consumer|O society|O instead|O .|O
According|O to|O Luther|I-PER 's|O notetaker|O Mathesius|I-PER ,|O Luther|I-PER thought|O the|O boy|O was|O a|O soulless|O mass|O of|O flesh|O possessed|O by|O the|O devil|O ,|O and|O suggested|O that|O he|O be|O suffocated|O .|O
Almost|O all|O the|O characteristics|O described|O in|O Kanner|I-PER 's|O first|O paper|O on|O the|O subject|O ,|O notably|O "|O autistic|O aloneness|O "|O and|O "|O insistence|O on|O sameness|O "|O ,|O are|O still|O regarded|O as|O typical|O of|O the|O autistic|O spectrum|O of|O disorders|O .|O
Kanner|I-PER 's|O reuse|O of|O autism|O led|O to|O decades|O of|O confused|O terminology|O like|O infantile|O schizophrenia|O ,|O and|O child|O psychiatry|O 's|O focus|O on|O maternal|O deprivation|O led|O to|O misconceptions|O of|O autism|O as|O an|O infant|O 's|O response|O to|O "|O refrigerator|O mothers|O "|O .|O
The|O Internet|I-MISC has|O helped|O autistic|O individuals|O bypass|O nonverbal|O cues|O and|O emotional|O sharing|O that|O they|O find|O so|O hard|O to|O deal|O with|O ,|O and|O has|O given|O them|O a|O way|O to|O form|O online|O communities|O and|O work|O remotely|O .|O
Another|O notable|O high|O albedo|O body|O is|O Eris|I-LOC ,|O with|O an|O albedo|O of|O 0.86|O .|O
Studies|O by|O the|O Hadley|I-ORG Centre|I-ORG have|O investigated|O the|O relative|O (|O generally|O warming|O )|O effect|O of|O albedo|O change|O and|O (|O cooling|O )|O effect|O of|O carbon|O sequestration|O on|O planting|O forests|O .|O
Over|O Antarctica|I-LOC they|O average|O a|O little|O more|O than|O 0.8|O .|O
The|O numeric|O character|O references|O in|O HTML|I-MISC and|O XML|I-MISC are|O "|O &|O #|O 65;|O "|O and|O "|O &|O #|O 97;|O "|O for|O upper|O and|O lower|O case|O ,|O respectively|O .|O
Alabama|I-LOC (|O i|O i|O i|O /|O l|O ə|O ˈ|O b|O æ|O m|O ə|O /|O )|O is|O a|O state|O located|O in|O the|O southeastern|O region|O of|O the|O United|I-LOC States|I-LOC of|I-LOC America|I-LOC .|O
It|O is|O bordered|O by|O Tenn.|I-LOC to|O the|O north|O ,|O Georgia|I-LOC to|O the|O east|O ,|O Florida|I-LOC and|O the|O Gulf|I-LOC of|I-LOC Mexico|I-LOC to|O the|O south|O ,|O and|O Mississippi|I-LOC to|O the|O west|O .|O
Alabama|I-LOC ranks|O 30th|O in|O total|O land|O area|O and|O ranks|O second|O in|O the|O size|O of|O its|O inland|O waterways|O .|O
Following|O World|I-MISC War|I-MISC II|I-MISC ,|O Alabama|I-LOC experienced|O growth|O as|O the|O economy|O of|O the|O state|O transitioned|O from|O agriculture|O to|O diversified|O interests|O in|O heavy|O manufacturing|O ,|O mineral|O extraction|O ,|O education|O ,|O and|O technology|O .|O
In|O addition|O ,|O the|O establishment|O or|O expansion|O of|O multiple|O military|O installations|O ,|O primarily|O those|O of|O the|O U.S.|I-ORG Army|I-ORG and|O U.S.|I-ORG Air|I-ORG Force|I-ORG ,|O added|O to|O state|O jobs|O .|O
The|O capital|O of|O Ala.|I-LOC is|O Montgomery|I-LOC .|O
The|O largest|O city|O by|O population|O is|O Birmingham|I-LOC .|O
The|O largest|O city|O by|O total|O land|O area|O is|O Huntsville|I-LOC .|O
Although|O the|O origin|O of|O Ala.|I-LOC could|O be|O discerned|O ,|O sources|O disagree|O on|O its|O meaning|O .|O
This|O notion|O was|O popularized|O in|O the|O 1850s|O through|O the|O writings|O of|O Alexander|I-PER Beaufort|I-PER Meek|I-PER .|O
Scholars|O believe|O the|O word|O comes|O from|O the|O Choctaw|I-MISC alba|O (|O meaning|O "|O plants|O "|O or|O "|O weeds|O "|O )|O and|O amo|O (|O meaning|O "|O to|O cut|O "|O ,|O "|O to|O trim|O "|O ,|O or|O "|O to|O gather|O "|O )|O .|O
Indigenous|O peoples|O of|O varying|O cultures|O lived|O in|O the|O area|O for|O thousands|O of|O years|O before|O European|I-MISC colonization|O .|O
Ala.|I-LOC was|O part|O of|O the|O new|O frontier|O in|O the|O 1820s|O and|O 1830s|O .|O
The|O economy|O of|O the|O central|O "|O Black|I-LOC Belt|I-LOC "|O was|O built|O around|O large|O cotton|O plantations|O whose|O owners|O built|O their|O wealth|O on|O slave|O labor|O .|O
While|O few|O battles|O were|O fought|O in|O the|O state|O ,|O Alabama|I-LOC contributed|O about|O 120,000|O soldiers|O to|O the|O American|I-MISC Civil|I-MISC War|I-MISC .|O
After|O the|O Civil|I-MISC War|I-MISC ,|O the|O state|O was|O still|O chiefly|O agricultural|O ,|O with|O an|O economy|O tied|O to|O cotton|O .|O
In|O 1900|O ,|O fourteen|O Black|I-LOC Belt|I-LOC counties|O had|O more|O than|O 79,000|O voters|O on|O the|O rolls|O .|O
The|O Voting|I-MISC Rights|I-MISC Act|I-MISC of|I-MISC 1965|I-MISC also|O protected|O the|O suffrage|O of|O poor|O whites|O .|O
The|O population|O growth|O rate|O in|O Ala.|I-LOC dropped|O by|O nearly|O half|O from|O 1910|O --|O 1920|O ,|O reflecting|O the|O effect|O of|O emigration|O .|O
At|O the|O same|O time|O ,|O many|O rural|O whites|O and|O blacks|O migrated|O to|O the|O city|O of|O Birmingham|I-LOC for|O work|O in|O new|O industrial|O jobs|O .|O
It|O experienced|O such|O rapid|O growth|O that|O it|O was|O nicknamed|O "|O The|O Magic|I-LOC City|I-LOC "|O .|O
By|O the|O 1920s|O ,|O Birmingham|I-LOC was|O the|O 19th|O largest|O city|O in|O the|O U.S.|I-LOC and|O held|O more|O than|O 30|O %|O of|O the|O population|O of|O the|O state|O .|O
In|O addition|O ,|O the|O state|O legislature|O gerrymandered|O the|O few|O Birmingham|I-LOC legislative|O seats|O to|O ensure|O election|O by|O persons|O living|O outside|O Birmingham|I-LOC .|O
One|O result|O was|O that|O Jefferson|I-LOC County|I-LOC ,|O containing|O Birmingham|I-LOC 's|O industrial|O and|O economic|O powerhouse|O ,|O contributed|O more|O than|O one-third|O of|O all|O tax|O revenue|O to|O the|O state|O ,|O but|O did|O not|O received|O a|O proportional|O amount|O in|O services|O .|O
A|O 1960|O study|O noted|O that|O because|O of|O rural|O domination|O ,|O "|O A|O minority|O of|O about|O 25|O per|O cent|O of|O the|O total|O state|O population|O is|O in|O majority|O control|O of|O the|O Alabama|I-ORG legislature|I-ORG .|O "|O
These|O factors|O created|O a|O longstanding|O tradition|O that|O any|O candidate|O who|O wanted|O to|O be|O viable|O with|O white|O voters|O had|O to|O run|O as|O a|O Democrat|I-ORG regardless|O of|O political|O beliefs|O .|O
Industrial|O development|O related|O to|O the|O demands|O of|O World|I-MISC War|I-MISC II|I-MISC brought|O prosperity|O .|O
In|O the|O 1960s|O under|O Governor|O George|I-PER Wallace|I-PER ,|O many|O whites|O in|O the|O state|O opposed|O integration|O efforts|O .|O
After|O 1972|O ,|O the|O state|O 's|O white|O voters|O shifted|O much|O of|O their|O support|O to|O Republican|I-MISC candidates|O in|O presidential|O elections|O (|O as|O also|O occurred|O in|O neighboring|O southern|O states|O )|O .|O
Since|O 1990|O the|O majority|O of|O whites|O in|O the|O state|O have|O voted|O increasingly|O Republican|I-MISC in|O state|O elections|O .|O
Democrats|I-ORG are|O still|O the|O majority|O party|O in|O both|O houses|O of|O the|O legislature|O .|O
Alabama|I-LOC is|O the|O thirtieth|O largest|O state|O in|I-ORG the|I-ORG United|I-ORG States|I-ORG with|O 52,423|O square|O miles|O (|O 135,775|O km²|O )|O of|O total|O area|O :|O 3.19|O %|O of|O the|O area|O is|O water|O ,|O making|O Ala.|I-LOC twenty-third|O in|O the|O amount|O of|O surface|O water|O ,|O also|O giving|O it|O the|O second|O largest|O inland|O waterway|O system|O in|I-ORG the|I-ORG United|I-ORG States|I-ORG .|O
About|O three-fifths|O of|O the|O land|O area|O is|O a|O gentle|O plain|O with|O a|O general|O descent|O towards|O the|O Mississippi|I-LOC River|I-LOC and|O the|O Gulf|I-LOC of|I-LOC Mexico|I-LOC .|O
The|O North|I-LOC Alabama|I-LOC region|O is|O mostly|O mountainous|O ,|O with|O the|O Tennessee|I-LOC River|I-LOC cutting|O a|O large|O valley|O creating|O numerous|O creeks|O ,|O streams|O ,|O rivers|O ,|O mountains|O ,|O and|O lakes|O .|O
The|O states|O bordering|O Alabama|I-LOC are|O Tennessee|I-LOC to|O the|O north|O ;|O Georgia|I-LOC to|O the|O east|O ;|O Florida|I-LOC to|O the|O south|O ;|O and|O Mississippi|I-LOC to|O the|O west|O .|O
Ala.|I-LOC has|O coastline|O at|O the|O Gulf|I-LOC of|I-LOC Mexico|I-LOC ,|O in|O the|O extreme|O southern|O edge|O of|O the|O state|O .|O
Alabama|I-LOC ranges|O in|O elevation|O from|O sea|O level|O at|O Mobile|I-LOC Bay|I-LOC to|O over|O 1,800|O feet|O (|O 550|O m|O )|O in|O the|O Appalachian|I-LOC Mountains|I-LOC in|O the|O northeast|O .|O
The|O highest|O point|O is|O Mount|I-LOC Cheaha|I-LOC ,|O at|O a|O height|O of|O 2407|O ft|O (|O 734|O m|O )|O .|O
Alabama|I-LOC 's|O land|O consists|O of|O 22|O million|O acres|O (|O 89000|O km|O 2|O )|O of|O forest|O or|O 67|O %|O of|O total|O land|O area|O .|O
Suburban|O Baldwin|I-LOC County|I-LOC ,|O along|O the|O Gulf|I-LOC Coast|I-LOC ,|O is|O the|O largest|O county|O in|O the|O state|O in|O both|O land|O area|O and|O water|O area|O .|O
Areas|O in|O Alabama|I-LOC administered|O by|O the|O National|I-ORG Park|I-ORG Service|I-ORG include|O Horseshoe|I-LOC Bend|I-LOC National|I-LOC Military|I-LOC Park|I-LOC near|O Alexander|I-LOC City|I-LOC ;|O Little|I-LOC River|I-LOC Canyon|I-LOC National|I-LOC Preserve|I-LOC near|O Fort|I-LOC Payne|I-LOC ;|O Russell|I-LOC Cave|I-LOC National|I-LOC Monument|I-LOC in|O Bridgeport|I-LOC ;|O Tuskegee|I-LOC Airmen|I-LOC National|I-LOC Historic|I-LOC Site|I-LOC in|O Tuskegee|I-LOC ;|O and|O Tuskegee|I-ORG Institute|I-ORG National|I-ORG Historic|I-ORG Site|I-ORG near|O Tuskegee|I-LOC .|O
A|O notable|O natural|O wonder|O in|O Alabama|I-LOC is|O "|I-LOC Natural|I-LOC Bridge|I-LOC "|I-LOC rock|O ,|O the|O longest|O natural|O bridge|O east|O of|O the|O Rockies|I-LOC ,|O located|O just|O south|O of|O Haleyville|I-LOC ,|O in|O Winston|I-LOC County|I-LOC .|O
A|O 5-mile|O (|O 8|O km|O )|O -wide|O meteorite|O impact|O crater|O is|O located|O in|O Elmore|I-LOC County|I-LOC ,|O just|O north|O of|O Montgomery|I-LOC .|O
This|O is|O the|O Wetumpka|I-LOC crater|I-LOC ,|O which|O is|O the|O site|O of|O "|O Alabama|I-LOC 's|O greatest|O natural|O disaster|O "|O .|O
The|O hills|O just|O east|O of|O downtown|O Wetumpka|I-LOC showcase|O the|O eroded|O remains|O of|O the|O impact|O crater|O that|O was|O blasted|O into|O the|O bedrock|O ,|O with|O the|O area|O labeled|O the|O Wetumpka|I-LOC crater|I-LOC or|O astrobleme|O (|O "|O star-wound|O "|O )|O because|O of|O the|O concentric|O rings|O of|O fractures|O and|O zones|O of|O shattered|O rock|O that|O can|O be|O found|O beneath|O the|O surface|O .|O
Temperatures|O tend|O to|O be|O warmer|O in|O the|O southern|O part|O of|O the|O state|O with|O its|O proximity|O to|O the|O Gulf|I-LOC of|I-LOC Mexico|I-LOC ,|O while|O the|O northern|O parts|O of|O the|O state|O ,|O especially|O in|O the|O Appalachian|I-LOC Mountains|I-LOC in|O the|O northeast|O ,|O tend|O to|O be|O slightly|O cooler|O .|O
Generally|O ,|O Ala.|I-LOC has|O very|O hot|O summers|O and|O mild|O winters|O with|O copious|O precipitation|O throughout|O the|O year|O .|O
Alabama|I-LOC receives|O an|O average|O of|O 56|O inches|O (|O 1400|O mm|O )|O of|O rainfall|O annually|O and|O enjoys|O a|O lengthy|O growing|O season|O of|O up|O to|O 300|O days|O in|O the|O southern|O part|O of|O the|O state|O .|O
Ala.|I-LOC is|O also|O prone|O to|O tropical|O storms|O and|O even|O hurricanes|O .|O
Areas|O of|O the|O state|O far|O away|O from|O the|O Gulf|I-LOC are|O not|O immune|O to|O the|O effects|O of|O the|O storms|O ,|O which|O often|O dump|O tremendous|O amounts|O of|O rain|O as|O they|O move|O inland|O and|O weaken|O .|O
Ala.|I-LOC ranks|O seventh|O in|O the|O number|O of|O deaths|O from|O lightning|O and|O ninth|O in|O the|O number|O of|O deaths|O from|O lightning|O strikes|O per|O capita|O .|O
The|O Super|I-MISC Outbreak|I-MISC in|O March|O 1974|O ,|O badly|O affected|O Alabama|I-LOC .|O
The|O northern|O part|O of|O the|O state|O --|O along|O the|O Tennessee|I-LOC Valley|I-LOC --|O is|O one|O of|O the|O areas|O in|O the|O US|I-LOC most|O vulnerable|O to|O violent|O tornadoes|O .|O
Alabama|I-LOC is|O one|O of|O the|O few|O places|O in|O the|O world|O that|O has|O a|O secondary|O tornado|O season|O (|O November|O and|O December|O )|O along|O with|O the|O spring|O severe|O weather|O season|O .|O
Although|O snow|O is|O a|O rare|O event|O in|O much|O of|O Ala.|I-LOC ,|O areas|O of|O the|O state|O north|O of|O Montgomery|I-LOC may|O receive|O a|O dusting|O of|O snow|O a|O few|O times|O every|O winter|O ,|O with|O an|O occasional|O moderately|O heavy|O snowfall|O every|O few|O years|O .|O
For|O example|O ,|O the|O annual|O average|O snowfall|O for|O the|O Birmingham|I-LOC area|O is|O 2|O inches|O per|O year|O .|O
In|O the|O southern|O Gulf|I-LOC coast|O ,|O snowfall|O is|O less|O frequent|O ,|O sometimes|O going|O several|O years|O without|O any|O snowfall|O .|O
The|O United|I-ORG States|I-ORG Census|I-ORG Bureau|I-ORG ,|O as|O of|O July|O 1|O ,|O 2008|O ,|O estimated|O Alabama|I-LOC 's|O population|O at|O 4,661,900|O ,|O which|O represents|O an|O increase|O of|O 214,545|O ,|O or|O 4.8|O %|O ,|O since|O the|O last|O census|O in|O 2000|O .|O
Immigration|O from|O outside|O the|O United|I-LOC States|I-LOC resulted|O in|O a|O net|O increase|O of|O 31,180|O people|O ,|O and|O migration|O within|O the|O country|O produced|O a|O net|O gain|O of|O 73,811|O people|O .|O
Working|O with|O Auburn|I-ORG University|I-ORG ,|O the|O tribe|O has|O begun|O a|O revival|O of|O the|O Cherokee|I-ORG language|O .|O
The|O Mobile|I-LOC area|O is|O notable|O for|O its|O large|O percentage|O of|O Catholics|I-MISC ,|O owing|O to|O the|O area|O 's|O founding|O as|O part|O of|O the|O French|I-MISC colony|O of|O La|I-LOC Louisiane|I-LOC and|O later|O history|O under|O Spanish|I-MISC rule|O .|O
The|O Southern|I-ORG Baptist|I-ORG Convention|I-ORG has|O the|O highest|O number|O of|O adherents|O in|O Alabama|I-LOC with|O 1,380,121|O ,|O followed|O by|O the|O United|I-ORG Methodist|I-ORG Church|I-ORG with|O 327,734|O members|O ,|O and|O the|O Catholic|I-PER Church|I-PER with|O 150,647|O adherents|O .|O
According|O to|O the|O United|I-LOC States|I-LOC Bureau|I-ORG of|I-ORG Economic|I-ORG Analysis|I-ORG ,|O the|O 2008|O total|O gross|O state|O product|O was|O $|O 170|O billion|O ,|O or|O $|O 29,411|O per|O capita|O .|O
Ala.|I-LOC 's|O agricultural|O outputs|O include|O poultry|O and|O eggs|O ,|O cattle|O ,|O plant|O nursery|O items|O ,|O peanuts|O ,|O cotton|O ,|O grains|O such|O as|O corn|O and|O sorghum|O ,|O vegetables|O ,|O milk|O ,|O soybeans|O ,|O and|O peaches|O .|O
Alabama|I-LOC 's|O industrial|O outputs|O include|O iron|O and|O steel|O products|O (|O including|O cast-iron|O and|O steel|O pipe|O )|O ;|O paper|O ,|O lumber|O ,|O and|O wood|O products|O ;|O mining|O (|O mostly|O coal|O )|O ;|O plastic|O products|O ;|O cars|O and|O trucks|O ;|O and|O apparel|O .|O
Ala.|I-LOC is|O part|O of|O the|O largest|O industrial|O growth|O corridor|O in|O the|O nation|O .|O
Alabama|I-LOC currently|O ranks|O 4th|O in|O the|O nation|O in|O automobile|O output|O .|O
In|O the|O 1970s|O and|O 1980s|O ,|O Birmingham|I-LOC 's|O economy|O was|O transformed|O by|O the|O University|I-ORG of|I-ORG Alabama|I-ORG at|I-ORG Birmingham|I-ORG (|O UAB|I-ORG )|O 's|O investments|O in|O bio-technology|O and|O medical|O research|O .|O
UAB|I-ORG is|O now|O the|O area|O 's|O largest|O employer|O and|O the|O largest|O in|O Alabama|I-LOC ,|O with|O a|O workforce|O of|O about|O 20,000|O .|O
Birmingham|I-LOC is|O also|O a|O leading|O U.S.|I-LOC banking|O center|O and|O the|O headquarters|O of|O Regions|I-ORG Financial|I-ORG Corporation|I-ORG ,|O BBVA|I-ORG Compass|I-ORG and|O Superior|I-ORG Bancorp|I-ORG .|O
In|O November|O 2006|O ,|O Regions|I-ORG Financial|I-ORG completed|O its|O merger|O with|O AmSouth|I-ORG Bancorporation|I-ORG ,|O which|O was|O also|O headquartered|O in|O Birmingham|I-LOC .|O
SouthTrust|I-ORG Corporation|I-ORG ,|O another|O large|O bank|O headquartered|O in|O Birmingham|I-LOC ,|O was|O acquired|O by|O Wachovia|I-ORG in|O 2004|O for|O $|O 14.3|O billion|O .|O
The|O city|O still|O has|O major|O operations|O for|O Wachovia|I-ORG and|O its|O now|O post-operating|O bank|O Wells|I-ORG Fargo|I-ORG ,|O which|O includes|O a|O regional|O headquarters|O ,|O a|O operations|O center|O campus|O and|O a|O $|O 400|O million|O dollar|O data|O center|O .|O
Birmingham|I-LOC also|O serves|O as|O the|O headquarters|O for|O several|O large|O investment|O management|O companies|O ,|O including|O Harbert|I-ORG Management|I-ORG Corporation|I-ORG .|O
Major|O insurance|O providers|O include|O Protective|I-ORG Life|I-ORG ,|O Infinity|I-ORG Property|I-ORG &|I-ORG Casualty|I-ORG ,|O Liberty|I-ORG National|I-ORG Life|I-ORG Insurance|I-ORG Company|I-ORG and|O ProAssurance|I-ORG .|O
Torchmark|I-ORG Corporation|I-ORG was|O headquartered|O in|O the|O city|O until|O 2006|O ,|O and|O still|O maintains|O its|O largest|O operation|O in|O the|O city|O .|O
Birmingham|I-LOC is|O also|O a|O powerhouse|O of|O construction|O and|O engineering|O companies|O .|O
Huntsville|I-LOC has|O a|O technology-driven|O economy|O ,|O a|O result|O of|O NASA|I-ORG 's|O Marshall|I-LOC Space|I-LOC Flight|I-LOC Center|I-LOC and|O the|O Redstone|I-LOC Arsenal|I-LOC .|O
Huntsville|I-LOC 's|O main|O economic|O influence|O is|O derived|O from|O aerospace|O and|O military|O technology|O .|O
Sanmina-SCI|I-ORG has|O a|O large|O presence|O in|O the|O area|O .|O
The|O Port|I-LOC of|I-LOC Mobile|I-LOC is|O currently|O the|O 9th|O largest|O by|O tonnage|O in|I-ORG the|I-ORG United|I-ORG States|I-ORG .|O
Alabama|I-LOC 's|O tax|O structure|O is|O one|O the|O most|O regressive|O in|I-ORG the|I-ORG United|I-ORG States|I-ORG .|O
Ala.|I-LOC levies|O a|O 2|O ,|O 4|O ,|O or|O 5|O percent|O personal|O income|O tax|O ,|O depending|O upon|O the|O amount|O earned|O and|O filing|O status|O ,|O though|O taxpayers|O can|O deduct|O their|O federal|O income|O tax|O from|O their|O Ala.|I-LOC state|O tax|O .|O
For|O example|O ,|O the|O total|O sales|O tax|O rate|O in|O Mobile|I-LOC is|O 9|O %|O and|O there|O is|O an|O additional|O restaurant|O tax|O of|O 1|O %|O ,|O which|O means|O that|O a|O diner|O in|O Mobile|I-LOC would|O pay|O a|O 10|O %|O tax|O on|O a|O meal|O .|O
Sales|O and|O excise|O taxes|O in|O Ala.|I-LOC account|O for|O 51|O percent|O of|O all|O state|O and|O local|O revenue|O ,|O compared|O with|O an|O average|O of|O about|O 36|O percent|O nationwide|O .|O
Ala.|I-LOC is|O also|O one|O of|O the|O few|O remaining|O states|O that|O levies|O a|O tax|O on|O food|O and|O medicine|O .|O
Alabama|I-LOC 's|O income|O tax|O on|O poor|O working|O families|O is|O among|O the|O nation|O 's|O very|O highest|O .|O
[|O citation|O needed|O ]|O Ala.|I-LOC is|O the|O only|O state|O that|O levies|O income|O tax|O on|O a|O family|O of|O four|O with|O income|O as|O low|O as|O $|O 4,600|O ,|O which|O is|O barely|O one-quarter|O of|O the|O federal|O poverty|O line|O .|O
[|O citation|O needed|O ]|O Alabama|I-LOC 's|O threshold|O is|O the|O lowest|O among|O the|O 41|O states|O and|O the|O District|I-LOC of|I-LOC Columbia|I-LOC with|O income|O taxes|O .|O
The|O overall|O federal|O ,|O state|O ,|O and|O local|O tax|O burden|O in|O Alabama|I-LOC ranks|O the|O state|O as|O the|O second|O least|O tax-burdened|O state|O in|O the|O country|O .|O
Property|O taxes|O are|O the|O lowest|O in|I-ORG the|I-ORG United|I-ORG States|I-ORG .|O
Since|O Alabama|I-LOC 's|O tax|O structure|O largely|O depends|O on|O consumer|O spending|O ,|O it|O is|O subject|O to|O high|O variable|O budget|O structure|O .|O
For|O example|O ,|O in|O 2003|O Alabama|I-LOC had|O an|O annual|O budget|O deficit|O as|O high|O as|O $|O 670|O million|O .|O
Another|O interstate|O road|O ,|O I-22|I-LOC ,|O is|O currently|O under|O construction|O .|O
When|O completed|O around|O 2012|O it|O will|O connect|O Birmingham|I-LOC with|O Memphis|I-LOC ,|O Tennessee|I-LOC .|O
Major|O airports|O in|O Alabama|I-LOC include|O Birmingham-Shuttlesworth|I-LOC International|I-LOC Airport|I-LOC (|O BHM|I-LOC )|O ,|O Huntsville|I-LOC International|I-LOC Airport|I-LOC (|O HSV|I-LOC )|O ,|O Dothan|I-LOC Regional|I-LOC Airport|I-LOC (|O DHN|I-LOC )|O ,|O Mobile|I-LOC Regional|I-LOC Airport|I-LOC (|O MOB|I-LOC )|O ,|O Montgomery|I-LOC Regional|I-LOC Airport|I-LOC ,|O Muscle|I-LOC Shoals|I-LOC --|I-LOC Northwest|I-LOC Alabama|I-LOC Regional|I-LOC Airport|I-LOC ,|O Tuscaloosa|I-LOC Regional|I-LOC Airport|I-LOC (|O TCL|I-LOC )|O ,|O and|O Pryor|I-LOC Field|I-LOC Regional|I-LOC Airport|I-LOC (|O DCU|I-LOC )|O .|O
There|O is|O a|O significant|O movement|O to|O rewrite|O and|O modernize|O Alabama|I-LOC 's|O constitution|O .|O
This|O movement|O is|O based|O upon|O the|O fact|O that|O Alabama|I-LOC 's|O constitution|O highly|O centralizes|O power|O in|O Montgomery|I-LOC and|O leaves|O practically|O no|O power|O in|O local|O hands|O .|O
Any|O policy|O changes|O proposed|O around|O the|O state|O must|O be|O approved|O by|O the|O entire|O Alabama|I-ORG legislature|I-ORG and|O ,|O frequently|O ,|O by|O state|O referendum|O .|O
Alabama|I-LOC is|O divided|O into|O three|O equal|O branches|O :|O The|O legislative|O branch|O is|O the|O Alabama|I-ORG Legislature|I-ORG ,|O a|O bicameral|O assembly|O composed|O of|O the|O Alabama|I-LOC House|I-LOC of|I-LOC Representatives|I-LOC ,|O with|O 105|O members|O ,|O and|O the|O Alabama|I-LOC Senate|I-LOC ,|O with|O 35|O members|O .|O
It|O is|O headed|O by|O the|O Governor|O of|O Alabama|I-LOC .|O
The|O highest|O court|O is|O the|O Supreme|I-LOC Court|I-LOC of|I-LOC Alabama|I-LOC .|O
Alabama|I-LOC has|O 67|O counties|O .|O
Alabama|I-LOC is|O an|O alcoholic|O beverage|O control|O state|O ;|O the|O government|O holds|O a|O monopoly|O on|O the|O sale|O of|O alcohol|O .|O
The|O current|O governor|O of|O the|O state|O is|O Republican|I-MISC Bob|I-PER Riley|I-PER .|O
The|O lieutenant|O governor|O is|O Jim|I-PER Folsom|I-PER Jr|I-PER .|O
The|O Chief|O Justice|O of|O the|O Alabama|I-LOC Supreme|I-LOC Court|I-LOC is|O Democrat|I-ORG Sue|I-PER Bell|I-PER Cobb|I-PER .|O
The|O Democratic|I-ORG Party|I-ORG currently|O holds|O a|O large|O majority|O in|O both|O houses|O of|O the|O Legislature|I-ORG .|O
The|O voters|O of|O the|O state|O revolted|O at|O what|O they|O perceived|O as|O disenfranchisement|O of|O their|O right|O to|O vote|O and|O elected|O the|O Republican|I-MISC challenger|O Guy|I-PER Hunt|I-PER as|O Governor|O .|O
Since|O then|O ,|O Republicans|I-MISC have|O become|O increasingly|O competitive|O in|O Ala.|I-LOC politics|O .|O
Republicans|I-MISC hold|O an|O 8|O --|O 1|O majority|O on|O the|O Alabama|I-LOC Supreme|I-LOC Court|I-LOC and|O have|O a|O 5|O --|O 2|O majority|O among|O statewide|O elected|O executive|O branch|O offices|O .|O
A|O majority|O of|O local|O offices|O in|O the|O state|O are|O still|O held|O by|O Democrats|I-ORG .|O
Alabama|I-LOC state|O politics|O gained|O nationwide|O and|O international|O attention|O in|O the|O 1950s|O and|O 1960s|O during|O the|O American|I-ORG Civil|I-ORG Rights|I-ORG Movement|I-ORG ,|O when|O majority|O whites|O bureaucratically|O ,|O and|O at|O times|O ,|O violently|O resisted|O protests|O for|O electoral|O and|O social|O reform|O .|O
George|I-PER Wallace|I-PER ,|O the|O state|O 's|O governor|O ,|O remains|O a|O notorious|O and|O controversial|O figure|O .|O
In|O 2007|O ,|O the|O Alabama|I-ORG Legislature|I-ORG passed|O ,|O and|O the|O Governor|O signed|O ,|O a|O resolution|O expressing|O "|O profound|O regret|O "|O over|O slavery|O and|O its|O lingering|O impact|O .|O
In|O 2004|O ,|O George|I-PER W.|I-PER Bush|I-PER won|O Alabama|I-LOC 's|O nine|O electoral|O votes|O by|O a|O margin|O of|O 25|O percentage|O points|O with|O 62.5|O %|O of|O the|O vote|O ,|O mostly|O white|O voters|O .|O
Public|O primary|O and|O secondary|O education|I-ORG in|I-ORG Alabama|I-ORG is|O under|O the|O overview|O of|O the|O Alabama|I-ORG State|I-ORG Board|I-ORG of|I-ORG Education|I-ORG as|O well|O as|O local|O oversight|O by|O 67|O county|O school|O boards|O and|O 60|O city|O boards|O of|O education|O .|O
While|O Alabama|I-LOC 's|O public|O education|O system|O has|O improved|O ,|O it|O lags|O behind|O in|O achievement|O compared|O to|O other|O states|O .|O
Alabama|I-LOC 's|O programs|O of|O higher|O education|O include|O 14|O four-year|O public|O universities|O ,|O two-year|O community|O colleges|O ,|O and|O 17|O private|O ,|O undergraduate|O and|O graduate|O universities|O .|O
In|O the|O state|O are|O two|O medical|O schools|O (|O University|I-ORG of|I-ORG Alabama|I-ORG at|I-ORG Birmingham|I-ORG and|O University|I-ORG of|I-ORG South|I-ORG Alabama|I-ORG )|O ,|O two|O veterinary|O colleges|O (|O Auburn|I-ORG University|I-ORG and|O Tuskegee|I-ORG University|I-ORG )|O ,|O a|O dental|O school|O (|O University|I-ORG of|I-ORG Alabama|I-ORG at|I-ORG Birmingham|I-ORG )|O ,|O an|O optometry|O college|O (|O University|I-ORG of|I-ORG Alabama|I-ORG at|I-ORG Birmingham|I-ORG )|O ,|O two|O pharmacy|O schools|O (|O Auburn|I-ORG University|I-ORG and|O Samford|I-ORG University|I-ORG )|O ,|O and|O five|O law|O schools|O (|O University|I-ORG of|I-ORG Alabama|I-ORG School|I-ORG of|I-ORG Law|I-ORG ,|O Birmingham|I-ORG School|I-ORG of|I-ORG Law|I-ORG ,|O Cumberland|I-ORG School|I-ORG of|I-ORG Law|I-ORG ,|O Miles|I-ORG Law|I-ORG School|I-ORG ,|O and|O the|O Thomas|I-ORG Goode|I-ORG Jones|I-ORG School|I-ORG of|I-ORG Law|I-ORG )|O .|O
Colleges|I-ORG and|I-ORG universities|I-ORG in|I-ORG Alabama|I-ORG offer|O degree|O programs|O from|O two-year|O associate|O degrees|O to|O 16|O doctoral|O level|O programs|O .|O
Achilles|I-PER also|O has|O the|O attributes|O of|O being|O the|O most|O handsome|O of|O the|O heroes|O assembled|O against|O Troy|I-LOC .|O
Later|O legends|O state|O that|O Achilles|I-PER was|O invulnerable|O in|O all|O of|O his|O body|O except|O for|O his|O heel|O .|O
Zeus|I-PER and|O Poseidon|I-PER had|O been|O rivals|O for|O the|O hand|O of|O Thetis|I-PER until|O Prometheus|I-PER ,|O the|O fire-bringer|O ,|O warned|O Zeus|I-PER of|O a|O prophecy|O that|O Thetis|I-PER would|O bear|O a|O son|O greater|O than|O his|O father|O .|O
For|O this|O reason|O ,|O the|O two|O gods|O withdrew|O their|O pursuit|O ,|O and|O had|O her|O wed|O Peleus|I-PER .|O
As|O with|O most|O mythology|O there|O is|O a|O tale|O which|O offers|O an|O alternative|O version|O of|O these|O events|O :|O in|O Argonautica|I-MISC (|O iv.760|O )|O Hera|I-PER alludes|O to|O Thetis|I-PER 's|O chaste|O resistance|O to|O the|O advances|O of|O Zeus|I-PER ,|O that|O Thetis|I-PER was|O so|O loyal|O to|O Hera|I-PER 's|O marriage|O bond|O that|O she|O coolly|O rejected|O him|O .|O
In|O another|O version|O of|O this|O story|O ,|O Thetis|I-PER anointed|O the|O boy|O in|O ambrosia|O and|O put|O him|O on|O top|O of|O a|O fire|O to|O burn|O away|O the|O mortal|O parts|O of|O his|O body|O .|O
She|O was|O interrupted|O by|O Peleus|I-PER and|O abandoned|O both|O father|O and|O son|O in|O a|O rage|O .|O
However|O none|O of|O the|O sources|O before|O Statius|I-PER makes|O any|O reference|O to|O this|O general|O invulnerability|O .|O
He|O cast|O two|O spears|O at|O once|O ,|O one|O grazed|O Achilles|I-PER '|I-PER elbow|O ,|O "|O drawing|O a|O spurt|O of|O blood|O .|O "|O
The|O first|O two|O lines|O of|O the|O Iliad|I-MISC read|O :|O
Achilles|I-PER '|I-PER consuming|O rage|O is|O at|O some|O times|O wavering|O ,|O but|O at|O other|O times|O he|O can|O not|O be|O cooled|O .|O
The|O humanization|O of|O Achilles|I-PER by|O the|O events|O of|O the|O war|O is|O an|O important|O theme|O of|O the|O narrative|O .|O
In|O the|O resulting|O battle|O ,|O Achilles|I-PER gave|O Telephus|I-PER a|O wound|O that|O would|O not|O heal|O ;|O Telephus|I-PER consulted|O an|O oracle|O ,|O who|O stated|O that|O "|O he|O that|O wounded|O shall|O heal|O "|O .|O
Achilles|I-PER refused|O ,|O claiming|O to|O have|O no|O medical|O knowledge|O .|O
Alternatively|O ,|O Telephus|I-PER held|O Orestes|I-PER for|O ransom|O ,|O the|O ransom|O being|O Achilles|I-PER '|I-PER aid|O in|O healing|O the|O wound|O .|O
Odysseus|I-PER reasoned|O that|O the|O spear|O had|O inflicted|O the|O wound|O ;|O therefore|O ,|O the|O spear|O must|O be|O able|O to|O heal|O it|O .|O
Pieces|O of|O the|O spear|O were|O scraped|O off|O onto|O the|O wound|O and|O Telephus|I-PER was|O healed|O .|O
Despite|O his|O youth|O ,|O he|O was|O one|O of|O the|O main|O Trojan|I-MISC war|I-MISC leaders|O .|O
Yet|O Achilles|I-PER ,|O struck|O by|O the|O beauty|O of|O both|O Troilus|I-PER and|O his|O sister|O Polyxena|I-PER ,|O and|O overcome|O with|O lust|O directed|O his|O sexual|O attentions|O on|O the|O youth|O --|O who|O refusing|O to|O yield|O found|O instead|O himself|O decapitated|O upon|O an|O altar-omphalos|O of|O Apollo|I-PER .|O
Later|O versions|O of|O the|O story|O suggested|O Troilus|I-PER was|O accidentally|O killed|O by|O Achilles|I-PER in|O an|O over-ardent|O lovers|O '|O embrace|O .|O
In|O this|O version|O of|O the|O myth|O ,|O Achilles|I-PER '|I-PER death|O therefore|O came|O in|O retribution|O for|O this|O sacrilege|O .|O
Ancient|O writers|O treated|O Troilus|I-PER as|O the|O epitome|O of|O a|O dead|O child|O mourned|O by|O his|O parents|O .|O
Homer|I-MISC 's|I-MISC Iliad|I-MISC is|O the|O most|O famous|O narrative|O of|O Achilles|I-PER '|I-PER deeds|O in|O the|O Trojan|I-MISC War|I-MISC .|O
The|O Homeric|I-PER epic|O only|O covers|O a|O few|O weeks|O of|O the|O war|O ,|O and|O does|O not|O narrate|O Achilles|I-PER '|I-PER death|O .|O
Agamemnon|I-PER had|O taken|O a|O woman|O named|O Chryseis|I-PER as|O his|O slave|O .|O
Her|O father|O Chryses|I-PER ,|O a|O priest|O of|O Apollo|I-PER ,|O begged|O Agamemnon|I-PER to|O return|O her|O to|O him|O .|O
The|O prophet|O Calchas|I-PER correctly|O determined|O the|O source|O of|O the|O troubles|O but|O would|O not|O speak|O unless|O Achilles|I-PER vowed|O to|O protect|O him|O .|O
Achilles|I-PER did|O so|O and|O Calchas|I-PER declared|O Chryseis|I-PER must|O be|O returned|O to|O her|O father|O .|O
Agamemnon|I-PER consented|O ,|O but|O then|O commanded|O that|O Achilles|I-PER '|I-PER battle|O prize|O Briseis|I-PER be|O brought|O to|O replace|O Chryseis|I-PER .|O
Agamemnon|I-PER agreed|O and|O sent|O Odysseus|I-PER and|O two|O other|O chieftains|O ,|O Ajax|I-PER and|O Phoenix|I-PER ,|O to|O Achilles|I-PER with|O the|O offer|O of|O the|O return|O of|O Briseis|I-PER and|O other|O gifts|O .|O
After|O receiving|O the|O news|O of|O the|O death|O of|O Patroclus|I-PER from|O Antilochus|I-PER ,|O the|O son|O of|O Nestor|I-PER ,|O Achilles|I-PER grieved|O over|O his|O cousin|O 's|O death|O and|O held|O many|O funeral|O games|O in|O his|O honor|O .|O
His|O mother|O Thetis|I-PER came|O to|O comfort|O the|O distraught|O Achilles|I-PER .|O
She|O persuaded|O Hephaestus|I-PER to|O make|O new|O armor|O for|O him|O ,|O in|O place|O of|O the|O armor|O that|O Patroclus|I-PER had|O been|O wearing|O which|O was|O taken|O by|O Hector|I-PER .|O
Enraged|O over|O the|O death|O of|O Patroclus|I-PER ,|O Achilles|I-PER ended|O his|O refusal|O to|O fight|O and|O took|O the|O field|O killing|O many|O men|O in|O his|O rage|O but|O always|O seeking|O out|O Hector|I-PER .|O
Achilles|I-PER even|O engaged|O in|O battle|O with|O the|O river|O god|O Scamander|I-PER who|O became|O angry|O that|O Achilles|I-PER was|O choking|O his|O waters|O with|O all|O the|O men|O he|O killed|O .|O
The|O god|O tried|O to|O drown|O Achilles|I-PER but|O was|O stopped|O by|O Hera|I-PER and|O Hephaestus|I-PER .|O
Finally|O Achilles|I-PER found|O his|O prey|O .|O
Achilles|I-PER chased|O Hector|I-PER around|O the|O wall|O of|I-LOC Troy|I-LOC three|O times|O before|O Athena|I-PER ,|O in|O the|O form|O of|O Hector|I-PER 's|O favorite|O and|O dearest|O brother|O ,|O Deiphobus|I-PER ,|O persuaded|O Hector|I-PER to|O stop|O running|O and|O fight|O Achilles|I-PER face|O to|O face|O .|O
After|O Hector|I-PER realized|O the|O trick|O ,|O he|O knew|O the|O battle|O was|O inevitable|O .|O
Wanting|O to|O go|O down|O fighting|O ,|O he|O charged|O at|O Achilles|I-PER with|O his|O only|O weapon|O ,|O his|O sword|O ,|O but|O missed|O .|O
Achilles|I-PER told|O Hector|I-PER it|O was|O hopeless|O to|O expect|O that|O of|O him|O ,|O declaring|O that|O "|O my|O rage|O ,|O my|O fury|O would|O drive|O me|O now|O to|O hack|O your|O flesh|O away|O and|O eat|O you|O raw|O --|O such|O agonies|O you|O have|O caused|O me|O "|O .|O
With|O the|O assistance|O of|O the|O god|O Hermes|I-PER ,|O Hector|I-PER 's|O father|O ,|O Priam|I-PER ,|O went|O to|O Achilles|I-PER '|I-PER tent|O to|O plead|O with|O Achilles|I-PER to|O permit|O him|O to|O perform|O for|O Hector|I-PER his|O funeral|O rites|O .|O
The|O final|O passage|O in|O the|O Iliad|I-MISC is|O Hector|I-PER 's|O funeral|O ,|O after|O which|O the|O doom|O of|I-LOC Troy|I-LOC was|O just|O a|O matter|O of|O time|O .|O
Achilles|I-PER ,|O after|O his|O temporary|O truce|O with|O Priam|I-PER ,|O fought|O and|O killed|O the|O Amazonian|I-MISC warrior|O queen|O Penthesilea|I-PER ,|O but|O later|O grieved|O over|O her|O death|O .|O
Following|O the|O death|O of|O Patroclus|I-PER ,|O Achilles|I-PER '|I-PER closest|O companion|O was|O Nestor|I-PER 's|O son|O Antilochus|I-PER .|O
Many|O Homeric|I-PER scholars|O argued|O that|O episode|O inspired|O many|O details|O in|O the|O Iliad|I-MISC 's|O description|O of|O the|O death|O of|O Patroclus|I-PER and|O Achilles|I-PER '|I-PER reaction|O to|O it|O .|O
The|O Aethiopis|I-MISC is|O now|O lost|O ,|O except|O for|O scattered|O fragments|O quoted|O by|O later|O authors|O .|O
As|O predicted|O by|O Hector|I-PER with|O his|O dying|O breath|O ,|O Achilles|I-PER was|O thereafter|O killed|O by|O Paris|I-PER with|O an|O arrow|O (|O to|O the|O heel|O according|O to|O Statius|I-PER )|O .|O
In|O some|O versions|O ,|O the|O god|O Apollo|I-PER guided|O Paris|I-PER '|O arrow|O .|O
Some|O retellings|O also|O state|O that|O Achilles|I-PER was|O scaling|O the|O gates|O of|I-LOC Troy|I-LOC and|O was|O hit|O with|O a|O poisoned|O arrow|O .|O
Both|O versions|O conspicuously|O deny|O the|O killer|O any|O sort|O of|O valor|O owing|O to|O the|O common|O conception|O that|O Paris|I-PER was|O a|O coward|O and|O not|O the|O man|O his|O brother|O Hector|I-PER was|O ,|O and|O Achilles|I-PER remained|O undefeated|O on|O the|O battlefield|O .|O
His|O bones|O were|O mingled|O with|O those|O of|O Patroclus|I-PER ,|O and|O funeral|O games|O were|O held|O .|O
Priam|I-PER is|O willing|O because|O it|O would|O mean|O the|O end|O of|O the|O war|O and|O an|O alliance|O with|O the|O world|O 's|O greatest|O warrior|O .|O
But|O while|O Priam|I-PER is|O overseeing|O the|O private|O marriage|O of|O Polyxena|I-PER and|O Achilles|I-PER ,|O Paris|I-PER who|O would|O have|O to|O give|O up|O Helen|I-PER if|O Achilles|I-PER married|O his|O sister|O hides|O in|O the|O bushes|O and|O shoots|O Achilles|I-PER with|O a|O divine|O arrow|O killing|O him|O .|O
Achilles|I-PER was|O cremated|O and|O his|O ashes|O buried|O in|O the|O same|O urn|O as|O those|O of|O Patroclus|I-PER .|O
Paris|I-PER was|O later|O killed|O by|O Philoctetes|I-PER using|O the|O enormous|O bow|O of|O Heracles|I-PER .|O
Achilles|I-PER '|I-PER armor|O was|O the|O object|O of|O a|O feud|O between|O Odysseus|I-PER and|O Telamonian|I-PER Ajax|I-PER (|O Ajax|I-PER the|O greater|O )|O .|O
Furious|O ,|O Ajax|I-PER cursed|O Odysseus|I-PER ,|O which|O earned|O the|O ire|O of|O Athena|I-PER .|O
Athena|I-PER temporarily|O made|O Ajax|I-PER so|O mad|O with|O grief|O and|O anguish|O that|O he|O began|O killing|O sheep|O ,|O thinking|O they|O are|O his|O comrades|O .|O
After|O a|O while|O ,|O when|O Athena|I-PER lifted|O his|O madness|O and|O Ajax|I-PER realized|O that|O he|O had|O actually|O been|O killing|O sheep|O ,|O he|O was|O so|O embarrassed|O that|O he|O committed|O suicide|O .|O
Odysseus|I-PER eventually|O gave|O the|O armor|O to|O Neoptolemus|I-PER ,|O the|O son|O of|O Achilles|I-PER .|O
The|O city|O was|O visited|O in|O 333|O BC|O by|O Alexander|I-PER the|I-PER Great|I-PER ,|O who|O envisioned|O himself|O as|O the|O new|O Achilles|I-PER and|O carried|O the|O Iliad|I-MISC with|O him|O ,|O but|O his|O court|O biographers|O do|O not|O mention|O the|O spear|O ,|O which|O he|O would|O indeed|O have|O touched|O with|O excitement|O .|O
Achilles|I-PER '|I-PER relationship|O with|O Patroclus|I-PER is|O a|O key|O aspect|O of|O his|O myth|O .|O
In|O the|O Iliad|I-MISC ,|O they|O appeared|O to|O be|O generally|O portrayed|O as|O a|O model|O of|O deep|O and|O loyal|O friendship|O .|O
Pausanias|I-PER has|O been|O told|O that|O the|O island|O is|O "|O covered|O with|O forests|O and|O full|O of|O animals|O ,|O some|O wild|O ,|O some|O tame|O .|O
In|O this|O island|O there|O is|O also|O Achilles|I-PER '|I-PER temple|O and|O his|O statue|O "|O .|O
This|O island|O is|O not|O inhabited|O ,|O and|O goats|O graze|O on|O it|O ,|O not|O many|O ,|O which|O the|O people|O who|O happen|O to|O arrive|O here|O with|O their|O ships|O ,|O sacrifice|O to|O Achilles|I-PER .|O
In|O this|O temple|O are|O also|O deposited|O a|O great|O many|O holy|O gifts|O ,|O craters|O ,|O rings|O and|O precious|O stones|O ,|O offered|O to|O Achilles|I-PER in|O gratitude|O .|O
Some|O of|O these|O are|O worded|O in|O Patroclus|I-PER '|O honor|O ,|O because|O those|O who|O wish|O to|O be|O favored|O by|O Achilles|I-PER ,|O honor|O Patroclus|I-PER at|O the|O same|O time|O .|O
There|O are|O also|O in|O this|O island|O countless|O numbers|O of|O sea|O birds|O ,|O which|O look|O after|O Achilles|I-PER '|I-PER temple|O .|O
Some|O of|O these|O animals|O they|O slaughter|O ,|O others|O they|O set|O free|O on|O the|O island|O ,|O in|O Achilles|I-PER '|I-PER honor|O .|O
As|O they|O have|O no|O sacrificial|O animals|O ,|O but|O wish|O to|O get|O them|O from|O the|O god|O of|O the|O island|O himself|O ,|O they|O consult|O Achilles|I-PER '|I-PER oracle|O .|O
To|O some|O of|O the|O people|O who|O come|O to|O this|O island|O ,|O Achilles|I-PER appears|O in|O dreams|O ,|O to|O others|O he|O would|O appear|O even|O during|O their|O navigation|O ,|O if|O they|O were|O not|O too|O far|O away|O ,|O and|O would|O instruct|O them|O as|O to|O which|O part|O of|O the|O island|O they|O would|O better|O anchor|O their|O ships|O "|O .|O
The|O heroic|O cult|O of|O Achilles|I-PER on|O Leuce|I-LOC island|O was|O widespread|O in|O antiquity|O ,|O not|O only|O along|O the|O sea|O lanes|O of|O the|O Pontic|I-LOC Sea|I-LOC but|O also|O in|O maritime|O cities|O whose|O economic|O interests|O were|O tightly|O connected|O to|O the|O riches|O of|O the|O Black|I-LOC Sea|I-LOC .|O
Leuce|I-LOC had|O also|O a|O reputation|O as|O a|O place|O of|O healing|O .|O
Ammianus|I-PER Marcellinus|I-PER attributes|O the|O healing|O to|O waters|O (|O aquae|O )|O on|O the|O island|O .|O
This|O elegant|O structure|O abounds|O with|O paintings|O and|O statues|O of|O Achilles|I-PER both|O in|O the|O main|O hall|O and|O in|O the|O lavish|O gardens|O depicting|O the|O heroic|O and|O tragic|O scenes|O of|O the|O Trojan|I-MISC war|I-MISC .|O
Achilles|I-PER '|I-PER role|O as|O the|O hero|O of|O grief|O forms|O an|O ironic|O juxtaposition|O with|O the|O conventional|O view|O of|O Achilles|I-PER as|O the|O hero|O of|O kleos|O (|O glory|O ,|O usually|O glory|O in|O war|O )|O .|O
Roman|O gladiatorial|O games|O often|O referenced|O classical|O mythology|O and|O this|O seems|O to|O reference|O Achilles|I-PER '|I-PER fight|O with|O Penthesilea|I-PER ,|O but|O give|O it|O an|O extra|O twist|O of|O Achilles|I-PER being|O '|O played|O '|O by|O a|O woman|O .|O
Some|O post-Homeric|I-PER sources|O claim|O that|O in|O order|O to|O keep|O Achilles|I-PER safe|O from|O the|O war|O ,|O Thetis|I-PER (|O or|O ,|O in|O some|O versions|O ,|O Peleus|I-PER )|O hides|O the|O young|O man|O at|O the|O court|O of|O Lycomedes|I-PER ,|O king|O of|O Skyros|I-LOC .|O
With|O Lycomedes|I-PER '|O daughter|O Deidamia|I-PER ,|O whom|O in|O the|O account|O of|O Statius|I-PER he|O rapes|O ,|O Achilles|I-PER there|O fathers|O a|O son|O ,|O Neoptolemus|I-PER (|O also|O called|O Pyrrhus|I-PER ,|O after|O his|O father|O 's|O possible|O alias|O )|O .|O
Odysseus|I-PER goes|O to|O Skyros|I-LOC in|O the|O guise|O of|O a|O peddler|O selling|O women|O 's|O clothes|O and|O jewelry|O and|O places|O a|O shield|O and|O spear|O among|O his|O goods|O .|O
In|O another|O version|O of|O the|O story|O ,|O Odysseus|I-PER arranges|O for|O a|O trumpet|O alarm|O to|O be|O sounded|O while|O he|O was|O with|O Lycomedes|I-PER '|O women|O ;|O while|O the|O women|O flee|O in|O panic|O ,|O Achilles|I-PER prepares|O to|O defend|O the|O court|O ,|O thus|O giving|O his|O identity|O away|O .|O
In|O book|O 11|O of|O Homer|I-PER 's|O Odyssey|I-MISC ,|O Odysseus|I-PER sails|O to|O the|O underworld|O and|O converses|O with|O the|O shades|O .|O
One|O of|O these|O is|O Achilles|I-PER ,|O who|O when|O greeted|O as|O "|O blessed|O in|O life|O ,|O blessed|O in|O death|O "|O ,|O responds|O that|O he|O would|O rather|O be|O a|O slave|O to|O the|O worst|O of|O masters|O than|O be|O king|O of|O all|O the|O dead|O .|O
But|O Achilles|I-PER then|O asks|O Odysseus|I-PER of|O his|O son|O 's|O exploits|O in|O the|O Trojan|I-MISC war|I-MISC ,|O and|O when|O Odysseus|I-PER tells|O of|O Neoptolemus|I-PER '|O heroic|O actions|O ,|O Achilles|I-PER is|O filled|O with|O satisfaction|O .|O
This|O leaves|O the|O reader|O with|O an|O ambiguous|O understanding|O of|O how|O Achilles|I-PER felt|O about|O the|O heroic|O life|O .|O
The|O kings|O of|O the|O Epirus|I-MISC claimed|O to|O be|O descended|O from|O Achilles|I-PER through|O his|O son|O ,|O Neoptolemus|I-PER .|O
In|O some|O versions|O of|O the|O myth|O ,|O Achilles|I-PER has|O a|O relationship|O with|O his|O captive|O Briseis|I-PER .|O
The|O tragedies|O relate|O the|O deeds|O of|O Achilles|I-PER during|O the|O Trojan|I-MISC War|I-MISC ,|O including|O his|O defeat|O of|O Hector|I-PER and|O eventual|O death|O when|O an|O arrow|O shot|O by|O Paris|I-PER and|O guided|O by|O Apollo|I-PER punctures|O his|O heel|O .|O
The|O role|O of|O Achilles|I-PER has|O been|O played|O by|O :|O
Achilles|I-PER has|O frequently|O been|O mentioned|O in|O music|O .|O
If|O Achilles|I-PER was|O anything|O ,|O he|O was|O a|O man|O who|O believed|O his|O own|O press|O releases.|O --|O Roger|I-PER Ebert|I-PER ,|O commenting|O on|O the|O classical|O depiction|O of|O Achilles|I-PER '|I-PER character|O and|O personality|O .|O
His|O tenure|O in|O office|O was|O occupied|O primarily|O with|O the|O defeat|O of|O the|O secessionist|O Confederate|I-LOC States|I-LOC of|I-LOC America|I-LOC in|O the|O American|I-MISC Civil|I-MISC War|I-MISC .|O
Lincoln|I-PER had|O closely|O supervised|O the|O victorious|O war|O effort|O ,|O especially|O the|O selection|O of|O top|O generals|O ,|O including|O Ulysses|I-PER S.|I-PER Grant|I-PER .|O
Lincoln|I-PER successfully|O defused|O the|O Trent|I-MISC affair|I-MISC ,|O a|O war|O scare|O with|O Britain|I-LOC late|O in|O 1861|O .|O
Copperheads|I-ORG and|O other|O opponents|O of|O the|O war|O criticized|O Lincoln|I-PER for|O refusing|O to|O compromise|O on|O the|O slavery|O issue|O .|O
Even|O with|O these|O opponents|O ,|O Lincoln|I-PER successfully|O rallied|O public|O opinion|O through|O his|O rhetoric|O and|O speeches|O ;|O his|O Gettysburg|I-PER Address|I-PER (|O 1863|O )|O became|O an|O iconic|O symbol|O of|O the|O nation|O 's|O duty|O .|O
Abraham|I-PER Lincoln|I-PER was|O born|O on|O February|O 12|O ,|O 1809|O ,|O to|O Thomas|I-PER Lincoln|I-PER and|O Nancy|I-PER Lincoln|I-PER (|O née|O Hanks|I-PER )|O ,|O two|O farmers|O ,|O in|O a|O one-room|O log|O cabin|O on|O the|O 348-acre|O (|O 1.4|O km|O 2|O )|O Sinking|I-LOC Spring|I-LOC Farm|I-LOC in|O southeast|O Hardin|I-LOC County|I-LOC ,|O Kentucky|I-LOC (|O now|O part|O of|O LaRue|I-LOC County|I-LOC )|O ,|O making|O him|O the|O first|O president|O born|O in|O the|O west|O .|O
Lincoln|I-PER was|O not|O given|O a|O middle|O name|O .|O
Thomas|I-PER Lincoln|I-PER was|O a|O respected|O citizen|O of|O rural|O Ky.|I-LOC .|O
He|O owned|O several|O farms|O ,|O including|O the|O Sinking|I-LOC Spring|I-LOC Farm|I-LOC ,|O although|O he|O was|O not|O wealthy|O .|O
Abraham|I-PER himself|O never|O joined|O their|O church|O ,|O or|O any|O other|O church|O .|O
Lincoln|I-PER later|O noted|O that|O this|O move|O was|O "|O partly|O on|O account|O of|O slavery,|O "|O and|O partly|O because|O of|O difficulties|O with|O land|O deeds|O in|O Kentucky|I-LOC .|O
Abraham|I-PER 's|O father|O disapproved|O of|O slavery|O on|O religious|O grounds|O and|O it|O was|O hard|O to|O compete|O economically|O with|O farms|O operated|O by|O slaves|O .|O
Unlike|O land|O in|O the|O Northwest|I-ORG Territory|I-ORG ,|O Kentucky|I-LOC never|O had|O a|O proper|O U.S.|I-LOC survey|O ,|O and|O farmers|O often|O had|O difficulties|O proving|O title|O to|O their|O property|O .|O
When|O Lincoln|I-PER was|O nine|O ,|O his|O mother|O ,|O then|O 34|O years|O old|O ,|O died|O of|O milk|O sickness|O .|O
Soon|O afterwards|O ,|O his|O father|O remarried|O ,|O to|O Sarah|I-PER Bush|I-PER Johnston|I-PER .|O
Lincoln|I-PER and|O his|O stepmother|O were|O close|O ;|O he|O called|O her|O "|O Mother|O "|O for|O the|O rest|O of|O his|O life|O ,|O but|O he|O became|O increasingly|O distant|O from|O his|O father|O .|O
Abraham|I-PER felt|O his|O father|O was|O not|O a|O success|O ,|O and|O did|O not|O want|O to|O be|O like|O him|O .|O
In|O 1830|O ,|O fearing|O a|O milk|O sickness|O outbreak|O ,|O the|O family|O settled|O on|O public|O land|O in|O Macon|I-LOC County|I-LOC ,|O Illinois|I-LOC .|O
Later|O that|O year|O ,|O hired|O by|O New|I-LOC Salem|I-LOC businessman|O Denton|I-PER Offutt|I-PER and|O accompanied|O by|O friends|O ,|O he|O took|O goods|O from|O New|I-LOC Salem|I-LOC to|O New|I-LOC Orleans|I-LOC via|O flatboat|O on|O the|O Sangamon|I-LOC ,|O Ill.|I-LOC and|O Mississippi|I-LOC rivers|O .|O
Lincoln|I-PER 's|O formal|O education|O consisted|O of|O about|O 18|O months|O of|O schooling|O ;|O but|O he|O was|O an|O avid|O reader|O and|O largely|O self-educated|O .|O
Lincoln|I-PER avoided|O hunting|O and|O fishing|O because|O he|O did|O not|O like|O killing|O animals|O ,|O even|O for|O food|O .|O
Lincoln|I-PER 's|O first|O love|O was|O Ann|I-PER Rutledge|I-PER .|O
He|O met|O her|O when|O he|O first|O moved|O to|O New|I-LOC Salem|I-LOC ,|O and|O by|O 1835|O they|O had|O reached|O a|O romantic|O understanding|O .|O
Rutledge|I-PER ,|O however|O ,|O died|O on|O August|O 25|O ,|O probably|O of|O typhoid|O fever|O .|O
In|O 1840|O ,|O Lincoln|I-PER became|O engaged|O to|O Mary|I-PER Todd|I-PER ,|O from|O a|O wealthy|O slaveholding|O family|O based|O in|O Lexington|I-LOC ,|O Ky.|I-LOC .|O
The|O Lincolns|I-PER soon|O had|O a|O budding|O family|O ,|O with|O the|O birth|O of|O son|O Robert|I-PER Todd|I-PER Lincoln|I-PER in|O Springfield|I-LOC ,|O Illinois|I-LOC on|O August|O 1|O ,|O 1843|O ,|O and|O second|O son|O Edward|I-PER Baker|I-PER Lincoln|I-PER on|O March|O 10|O ,|O 1846|O ,|O also|O in|O Springfield|I-LOC .|O
According|O to|O a|O house|O girl|O ,|O Abraham|I-PER "|O was|O remarkably|O fond|O of|O children|O .|O "|O
The|O Lincolns|I-PER did|O not|O believe|O in|O strict|O rules|O and|O tight|O boundaries|O when|O it|O came|O to|O their|O children|O .|O
Robert|I-MISC ,|O however|O ,|O would|O be|O the|O only|O one|O of|O the|O Lincolns|I-PER '|O children|O to|O survive|O into|O adulthood|O .|O
Edward|I-PER Lincoln|I-PER died|O on|O February|O 1|O ,|O 1850|O in|O Springfield|I-LOC ,|O likely|O of|O tuberculosis|O .|O
The|O Lincolns|I-PER '|O grief|O over|O this|O loss|O was|O somewhat|O assuaged|O by|O the|O birth|O of|O William|I-PER "|I-PER Willie|I-PER "|I-PER Wallace|I-PER Lincoln|I-PER nearly|O eleven|O months|O later|O ,|O on|O December|O 21|O .|O
But|O Willie|I-PER himself|O died|O of|O a|O fever|O at|O the|O age|O of|O eleven|O on|O February|O 20|O ,|O 1862|O ,|O in|O Washington|I-LOC ,|O D.C.|I-LOC ,|O during|O President|O Lincoln|I-PER 's|O first|O term|O .|O
The|O Lincolns|I-PER '|O fourth|O son|O Thomas|I-PER "|I-PER Tad|I-PER "|I-PER Lincoln|I-PER was|O born|O on|O April|O 4|O ,|O 1853|O ,|O and|O ,|O although|O he|O outlived|O his|O father|O ,|O died|O at|O the|O age|O of|O eighteen|O on|O July|O 16|O ,|O 1871|O in|O Chicago|I-LOC .|O
Robert|I-PER Lincoln|I-PER eventually|O went|O on|O to|O attend|O Phillips|I-ORG Exeter|I-ORG Academy|I-ORG and|O Harvard|I-ORG College|I-ORG .|O
His|O (|O and|O by|O extension|O ,|O his|O father|O 's|O )|O last|O known|O lineal|O descendant|O ,|O Robert|I-PER Todd|I-PER Lincoln|I-PER Beckwith|I-PER ,|O died|O December|O 24|O ,|O 1985|O .|O
Later|O in|O life|O ,|O Mary|I-PER Todd|I-PER Lincoln|I-PER found|O herself|O unable|O to|O cope|O with|O the|O stresses|O of|O losing|O her|O husband|O and|O sons|O ,|O and|O this|O (|O in|O conjunction|O with|O what|O some|O historians|O consider|O to|O have|O been|O pre-existing|O bipolar|O disorder|O )|O eventually|O led|O Robert|I-PER Lincoln|I-PER to|O involuntarily|O commit|O her|O to|O a|O mental|O health|O asylum|O in|O 1875|O .|O
Abraham|I-PER Lincoln|I-PER himself|O was|O contemporaneously|O described|O as|O suffering|O from|O "|O melancholy|O "|O throughout|O his|O legal|O and|O political|O life|O ,|O a|O condition|O which|O modern|O mental|O health|O professionals|O would|O now|O typically|O characterize|O as|O clinical|O depression|O .|O
Lincoln|I-PER began|O his|O political|O career|O in|O March|O 1832|O at|O age|O 23|O when|O he|O announced|O his|O candidacy|O for|O the|O Illinois|I-ORG General|I-ORG Assembly|I-ORG .|O
He|O was|O esteemed|O by|O the|O residents|O of|O New|I-LOC Salem|I-LOC ,|O but|O he|O did|O not|O have|O an|O education|O ,|O powerful|O friends|O ,|O or|O money|O .|O
The|O centerpiece|O of|O his|O platform|O was|O the|O undertaking|O of|O navigational|O improvements|O on|O the|O Sangamon|I-LOC River|I-LOC .|O
Before|O the|O election|O he|O served|O as|O a|O captain|O in|O a|O company|O of|O the|O Illinois|I-LOC militia|O during|O the|O Black|I-PER Hawk|I-PER War|I-PER ,|O although|O he|O never|O saw|O combat|O .|O
Lincoln|I-PER returned|O from|O the|O militia|O after|O a|O few|O months|O and|O was|O able|O to|O campaign|O throughout|O the|O county|O before|O the|O August|O 6|O election|O .|O
When|O the|O votes|O were|O counted|O ,|O Lincoln|I-PER finished|O eighth|O out|O of|O thirteen|O candidates|O (|O only|O the|O top|O four|O were|O elected|O )|O ,|O but|O he|O did|O manage|O to|O secure|O 277|O out|O of|O the|O 300|O votes|O cast|O in|O the|O New|I-LOC Salem|I-LOC precinct|O .|O
He|O was|O labeled|O a|O Whig|I-ORG ,|O but|O ran|O a|O bipartisan|O campaign|O .|O
He|O then|O decided|O to|O become|O a|O lawyer|O ,|O and|O began|O teaching|O himself|O law|O by|O reading|O Commentaries|I-MISC on|I-MISC the|I-MISC Laws|I-MISC of|I-MISC England|I-MISC .|O
Admitted|O to|O the|O bar|O in|O 1837|O ,|O he|O moved|O to|O Springfield|I-LOC ,|O Illinois|I-LOC ,|O that|O April|O ,|O and|O began|O to|O practice|O law|O with|O John|I-PER T.|I-PER Stuart|I-PER ,|O Mary|I-PER Todd|I-PER 's|O cousin|O ,|O who|O let|O Lincoln|I-PER have|O the|O run|O of|O his|O law|O library|O while|O studying|O to|O be|O a|O lawyer|O .|O
With|O a|O reputation|O as|O a|O formidable|O adversary|O during|O cross-examinations|O and|O closing|O arguments|O ,|O Lincoln|I-PER became|O an|O able|O and|O successful|O lawyer|O .|O
In|O 1841|O ,|O Lincoln|I-PER entered|O law|O practice|O with|O William|I-PER Herndon|I-PER ,|O whom|O Lincoln|I-PER thought|O "|O a|O studious|O young|O man|O .|O "|O
He|O served|O four|O successive|O terms|O in|O the|O Illinois|I-LOC House|I-LOC of|I-LOC Representatives|I-LOC as|O a|O representative|O from|O Sangamon|I-LOC County|I-LOC ,|O affiliated|O with|O the|O Whig|I-ORG party|O .|O
Lincoln|I-PER was|O a|O Whig|I-ORG ,|O and|O since|O the|O early|O 1830s|O had|O strongly|O admired|O the|O policies|O and|O leadership|O of|O Henry|I-PER Clay|I-PER .|O
"|O I|O have|O always|O been|O an|O old-line|O Henry|I-PER Clay|I-PER Whig|I-ORG "|O he|O professed|O to|O friends|O in|O 1861|O .|O
He|O used|O his|O office|O as|O an|O opportunity|O to|O speak|O out|O against|O the|O Mexican|I-MISC --|I-MISC American|I-MISC War|I-MISC ,|O which|O he|O attributed|O to|O President|O Polk|I-PER 's|O desire|O for|O "|O military|O glory|O --|O that|O attractive|O rainbow|O ,|O that|O rises|O in|O showers|O of|O blood|O .|O "|O
Lincoln|I-PER 's|O main|O stand|O against|O Polk|I-PER occurred|O in|O his|O Spot|I-ORG Resolutions|I-ORG :|O The|O war|O had|O begun|O with|O a|O violent|O confrontation|O on|O territory|O disputed|O by|O Mexico|I-MISC and|O Tex.|I-LOC ,|O but|O as|O Lincoln|I-PER pointed|O out|O ,|O Polk|I-PER had|O insisted|O that|O Mexican|I-MISC soldiers|O had|O "|O invaded|O our|O territory|O and|O shed|O the|O blood|O of|O our|O fellow-citizens|O on|O our|O own|O soil|O .|O "|O
Congress|O never|O enacted|O the|O resolution|O or|O even|O debated|O it|O ,|O and|O its|O introduction|O resulted|O in|O a|O loss|O of|O political|O support|O for|O Lincoln|I-PER in|O his|O district|O ;|O one|O Ill.|I-LOC newspaper|O derisively|O nicknamed|O him|O "|O spotty|O Lincoln|I-PER .|O "|O
Taylor|I-PER won|O and|O his|O administration|O offered|O him|O the|O governorship|O of|O the|O Oregon|I-LOC Territory|I-LOC .|O
The|O territory|O leaned|O heavily|O Democratic|I-MISC ,|O and|O Lincoln|I-PER doubted|O they|O would|O elect|O him|O as|O governor|O or|O as|O a|O senator|O after|O they|O were|O admitted|O to|O the|O union|O ,|O so|O he|O returned|O to|O Springfield|I-LOC without|O any|O appointment|O .|O
Back|O in|O Springfield|I-LOC ,|O Lincoln|I-PER turned|O most|O of|O his|O energies|O to|O making|O a|O living|O practicing|O law|O ,|O handling|O "|O every|O kind|O of|O business|O that|O could|O come|O before|O a|O prairie|O lawyer|O .|O "|O
His|O reputation|O grew|O ,|O and|O he|O appeared|O before|O the|O Supreme|I-ORG Court|I-ORG of|I-ORG the|I-ORG United|I-ORG States|I-ORG ,|O arguing|O a|O case|O involving|O a|O canal|O boat|O that|O sank|O after|O hitting|O a|O bridge|O .|O
Lincoln|I-PER represented|O numerous|O transportation|O interests|O ,|O such|O as|O the|O river|O barges|O and|O the|O railroads|O .|O
As|O a|O riverboat|O man|O ,|O Lincoln|I-PER had|O initially|O favored|O riverboat|O interests|O ,|O but|O ultimately|O he|O represented|O whoever|O hired|O him|O .|O
Lincoln|I-PER 's|O goal|O had|O been|O to|O lessen|O the|O draft|O of|O a|O river|O craft|O by|O pushing|O horizontal|O floats|O into|O the|O water|O alongside|O the|O hull|O .|O
The|O idea|O was|O never|O commercialized|O ,|O but|O Lincoln|I-PER is|O still|O the|O only|O person|O to|O hold|O a|O patent|O and|O serve|O as|O President|O of|O the|O United|I-LOC States|I-LOC .|O
He|O won|O this|O case|O ,|O and|O the|O decision|O by|O the|O Illinois|I-LOC Supreme|I-LOC Court|I-LOC was|O eventually|O cited|O by|O 25|O other|O courts|O throughout|O the|O United|I-LOC States|I-LOC .|O
Lincoln|I-PER appeared|O in|O front|O of|O the|O Illinois|I-LOC Supreme|I-LOC Court|I-LOC 175|O times|O ,|O 51|O times|O as|O sole|O counsel|O ,|O of|O which|O ,|O 31|O were|O decided|O in|O his|O favor|O .|O
The|O case|O is|O famous|O for|O Lincoln|I-PER 's|O use|O of|O judicial|O notice|O to|O show|O an|O eyewitness|O had|O lied|O on|O the|O stand|O .|O
After|O the|O witness|O testified|O to|O having|O seen|O the|O crime|O in|O the|O moonlight|O ,|O Lincoln|I-PER produced|O a|O Farmers|I-MISC '|I-MISC Almanac|I-MISC to|O show|O that|O the|O moon|O on|O that|O date|O was|O at|O such|O a|O low|O angle|O it|O could|O not|O have|O produced|O enough|O illumination|O to|O see|O anything|O clearly|O .|O
Based|O on|O this|O evidence|O ,|O Armstrong|I-PER was|O acquitted|O .|O
Lincoln|I-PER returned|O to|O politics|O in|O response|O to|O the|O Kansas-Nebraska|I-MISC Act|I-MISC (|O 1854|O )|O ,|O which|O expressly|O repealed|O the|O limits|O on|O slavery|O 's|O extent|O as|O established|O by|O the|O Missouri|I-MISC Compromise|I-MISC (|O 1820|O )|O .|O
On|O October|O 16|O ,|O 1854|O ,|O "|O Peoria|I-MISC Speech|I-MISC ,|O "|O Lincoln|I-PER outlined|O his|O position|O on|O slavery|O that|O he|O would|O repeat|O over|O the|O next|O six|O years|O on|O the|O route|O to|O the|O presidency|O .|O
According|O to|O a|O newspaper|O account|O of|O the|O speech|O ,|O Lincoln|I-PER spoke|O with|O "|O a|O thin|O high-pitched|O falsetto|O voice|O of|O much|O carrying|O power|O ,|O that|O could|O be|O heard|O a|O long|O distance|O in|O spite|O of|O the|O hustle|O and|O bustle|O of|O the|O crowd|O ...|O [|O with|O ]|O the|O accent|O and|O pronunciation|O peculiar|O to|O his|O native|O state|O ,|O Kentucky|I-LOC .|O "|O
Trumbull|I-PER beat|O Matteson|I-PER in|O the|O tenth|O round|O of|O voting|O .|O
The|O Whigs|I-ORG had|O been|O irreparably|O split|O by|O the|O Kansas-Nebraska|I-MISC Act|I-MISC .|O
"|O I|O think|O I|O am|O a|O Whig|I-ORG ,|O but|O others|O say|O there|O are|O not|O Whigs|I-ORG ,|O and|O I|O am|O an|O abolitionist|O ,|O even|O though|O I|O do|O no|O more|O than|O oppose|O the|O expansion|O of|O slavery|O "|O he|O said|O .|O
At|O the|O Republican|I-ORG convention|I-ORG in|O 1856|O ,|O Lincoln|I-PER placed|O second|O in|O the|O contest|O to|O become|O the|O party|O 's|O candidate|O for|O Vice-President|O .|O
In|O 1857|O --|O 58|O ,|O Douglas|I-PER broke|O with|O President|O Buchanan|I-PER ,|O leading|O to|O a|O fight|O for|O control|O of|O the|O Democratic|I-ORG Party|I-ORG .|O
'|O (|O Mark|I-MISC 3:25|O )|O I|O believe|O this|O government|O can|O not|O endure|O permanently|O half|O slave|O and|O half|O free|O .|O
The|O speech|O created|O an|O evocative|O image|O of|O the|O danger|O of|O disunion|O caused|O by|O the|O slavery|O debate|O ,|O and|O rallied|O Republicans|I-MISC across|O the|O north|O .|O
The|O 1858|O campaign|O featured|O the|O Lincoln|I-PER --|O Douglas|I-PER debates|O ,|O generally|O considered|O the|O most|O famous|O political|O debate|O in|O American|I-ORG history|I-ORG .|O
Nevertheless|O ,|O Lincoln|I-PER 's|O definition|O of|O the|O issues|O gave|O him|O a|O national|O political|O reputation|O .|O
In|O one|O of|O the|O most|O important|O speeches|O of|O his|O career|O ,|O Lincoln|I-PER showed|O that|O he|O was|O a|O contender|O for|O the|O Republican|I-MISC 's|O presidential|O nomination|O .|O
At|O this|O convention|O ,|O Lincoln|I-PER received|O his|O first|O endorsement|O to|O run|O for|O the|O presidency|O .|O
On|O May|O 18|O ,|O at|O the|O 1860|I-MISC Republican|I-MISC National|I-MISC Convention|I-MISC in|O Chicago|I-LOC ,|O Lincoln|I-PER emerged|O as|O the|O Republican|I-MISC candidate|O on|O the|O third|O ballot|O ,|O beating|O candidates|O such|O as|O William|I-PER H.|I-PER Seward|I-PER and|O Salmon|I-PER P.|I-PER Chase|I-PER .|O
Why|O Lincoln|I-PER won|O the|O nomination|O has|O been|O subject|O of|O much|O debate|O .|O
His|O expressed|O views|O on|O slavery|O were|O seen|O as|O more|O moderate|O than|O those|O of|O rivals|O Seward|I-PER and|O Chase|I-PER .|O
Some|O feel|O that|O Seward|I-PER lost|O more|O than|O Lincoln|I-PER won|O ,|O including|O Seward|I-PER himself|O .|O
Others|O attribute|O it|O to|O luck|O ,|O and|O the|O fact|O that|O the|O convention|O was|O held|O in|O Lincoln|I-PER 's|O home|O state|O .|O
Historian|O Doris|I-PER Kearns|I-PER Goodwin|I-PER believes|O the|O real|O reason|O was|O Lincoln|I-PER 's|O skill|O as|O a|O politician|O .|O
Throughout|O the|O 1850s|O Lincoln|I-PER denied|O that|O there|O would|O ever|O be|O a|O civil|O war|O ,|O and|O his|O supporters|O repeatedly|O rejected|O claims|O that|O his|O election|O would|O incite|O secession|O .|O
Meanwhile|O ,|O Douglas|I-PER was|O selected|O as|O the|O candidate|O of|O the|O northern|O Democrats|I-ORG ,|O with|O Herschel|I-PER Vespasian|I-PER Johnson|I-PER as|O the|O vice-presidential|O candidate|O .|O
As|O Douglas|I-PER stumped|O the|O country|O ,|O Lincoln|I-PER was|O the|O only|O one|O of|O the|O four|O major|O candidates|O to|O give|O no|O speeches|O whatever|O .|O
There|O were|O thousands|O of|O Republican|I-MISC speakers|O who|O focused|O first|O on|O the|O party|O platform|O ,|O and|O second|O on|O Lincoln|I-PER 's|O life|O story|O ,|O emphasizing|O his|O childhood|O poverty|O .|O
A|O Chicago|I-ORG Tribune|I-ORG writer|O produced|O a|O pamphlet|O that|O detailed|O Lincoln|I-PER 's|O life|O ,|O and|O sold|O one|O million|O copies|O .|O
It|O was|O during|O this|O campaign|O that|O Lincoln|I-PER became|O the|O first|O President|O to|O have|O placed|O his|O photo|O on|O a|O campaign|O button|O .|O
Lincoln|I-PER received|O 1,866,452|O votes|O ,|O Douglas|I-PER 1,376,957|O votes|O ,|O Breckinridge|I-PER 849,781|O votes|O ,|O and|O Bell|I-PER 588,789|O votes|O .|O
The|O electoral|O vote|O was|O decisive|O :|O Lincoln|I-PER had|O 180|O and|O his|O opponents|O added|O together|O had|O only|O 123|O .|O
Bell|I-PER won|O Va.|I-LOC ,|O Tenn.|I-LOC ,|O and|O Kentucky|I-LOC ,|O and|O Breckinridge|I-PER won|O the|O rest|O of|O the|O South|I-MISC .|O
Yet|O the|O Democrats|I-ORG suffered|O a|O significant|O reverse|O in|O the|O electoral|O realignment|O of|O the|O mid-1850s|O ;|O they|O lost|O the|O dominance|O they|O had|O achieved|O over|O the|O Whig|I-ORG Party|I-ORG and|O ,|O indeed|O ,|O were|O the|O minority|O party|O in|O most|O of|O the|O northern|O states|O .|O
Abraham|I-PER Lincoln|I-PER 's|O election|O was|O a|O watershed|O in|O the|O balance|O of|O power|O of|O competing|O national|O and|O parochial|O interests|O and|O affiliations|O .|O
On|O December|O 20|O ,|O 1860|O ,|O S.C.|I-LOC took|O the|O lead|O ;|O by|O February|O 1|O ,|O 1861|O ,|O Florida|I-ORG ,|O Mississippi|I-LOC ,|O Alabama|I-MISC ,|O Georgia|I-LOC ,|O Louisiana|I-LOC ,|O and|O Tex.|I-LOC had|O followed|O .|O
The|O seven|O states|O soon|O declared|O themselves|O to|O be|O a|O new|O nation|O ,|O the|O Confederate|I-LOC States|I-LOC of|I-LOC America|I-LOC .|O
The|O upper|O South|I-MISC (|O Delaware|I-LOC ,|O Maryland|I-LOC ,|O Virginia|I-LOC ,|O N.C.|I-LOC ,|O Tennessee|I-LOC ,|O Ky.|I-LOC ,|O Missouri|I-LOC ,|O and|O Arkansas|I-LOC )|O listened|O to|O ,|O but|O initially|O rejected|O ,|O the|O secessionist|O appeal|O .|O
President|O Buchanan|I-PER and|O President-elect|O Lincoln|I-PER refused|O to|O recognize|O the|O Confederacy|I-LOC .|O
Attempts|O at|O compromise|O ,|O such|O as|O the|O Crittenden|I-MISC Compromise|I-MISC which|O would|O have|O extended|O the|O Missouri|I-MISC line|I-MISC of|I-MISC 1820|I-MISC ,|O were|O discussed|O .|O
would|O lose|O us|O everything|O we|O gained|O in|O the|O election|O ;|O that|O filibustering|O for|O all|O South|I-MISC of|O us|O ,|O and|O making|O slave|O states|O of|O it|O ,|O would|O follow|O in|O spite|O of|O us|O ,|O under|O either|O plan,|O "|O while|O another|O Republican|I-MISC Congressman|O warned|O it|O "|O would|O amount|O to|O a|O perpetual|O covenant|O of|O war|O against|O every|O people|O ,|O tribe|O ,|O and|O state|O owning|O a|O foot|O of|O land|O between|O here|O and|O Tierra|I-LOC del|I-LOC Fuego|I-LOC .|O "|O
The|O Confederate|I-LOC States|I-LOC of|I-LOC America|I-LOC selected|O Jefferson|I-PER Davis|I-PER on|O February|O 9|O ,|O 1861|O ,|O as|O their|O provisional|O President|O .|O
This|O amendment|O ,|O which|O explicitly|O protected|O slavery|O in|O those|O states|O in|O which|O it|O already|O existed|O ,|O was|O considered|O by|O Lincoln|I-PER to|O be|O a|O possible|O way|O to|O stave|O off|O secession|O .|O
The|O failure|O of|O the|O Peace|I-ORG Conference|I-ORG of|I-ORG 1861|I-ORG rendered|O legislative|O compromise|O virtually|O impossible|O .|O
Buchanan|I-PER might|O have|O allowed|O the|O southern|O states|O to|O secede|O ,|O and|O some|O members|O of|O his|O cabinet|O recommended|O that|O .|O
However|O ,|O conservative|O Democratic|I-MISC nationalists|O ,|O such|O as|O Jeremiah|I-PER S.|I-PER Black|I-PER ,|O Joseph|I-PER Holt|I-PER ,|O and|O Edwin|I-PER M.|I-PER Stanton|I-PER had|O taken|O control|O of|O Buchanan|I-PER 's|O cabinet|O in|O early|O January|O ,|O and|O refused|O to|O accept|O secession|O .|O
North|I-LOC Carolina|I-LOC ,|O Tennessee|I-LOC ,|O and|O Arkansas|I-LOC also|O voted|O for|O secession|O over|O the|O next|O two|O months|O .|O
Missouri|I-LOC ,|O Kentucky|I-LOC and|O Maryland|I-LOC threatened|O secession|O ,|O but|O neither|O they|O nor|O the|O slave|O state|O of|O Delaware|I-LOC seceded|O .|O
George|I-PER William|I-PER Brown|I-PER ,|O the|O Mayor|O of|O Baltimore|I-LOC ,|O and|O other|O suspect|O Maryland|I-LOC politicians|O were|O arrested|O and|O imprisoned|O at|O Fort|I-LOC McHenry|I-LOC .|O
Rebel|I-LOC leaders|O were|O also|O arrested|O and|O held|O in|O military|O prisons|O without|O trial|O .|O
One|O ,|O Clement|I-PER Vallandigham|I-PER ,|O was|O exiled|O ,|O but|O the|O remainder|O were|O released|O ,|O usually|O after|O two|O or|O three|O months|O .|O
Despite|O his|O inexperience|O in|O military|O affairs|O ,|O Lincoln|I-PER immediately|O took|O an|O active|O part|O in|O determining|O war|O strategy|O .|O
McClellan|I-PER ,|O a|O youthful|O West|I-ORG Point|I-ORG graduate|O and|O railroad|O executive|O called|O back|O to|O active|O military|O service|O ,|O took|O a|O more|O cautious|O approach|O .|O
Lincoln|I-PER insisted|O on|O holding|O some|O of|O McClellan|I-PER 's|O troops|O to|O defend|O the|O capital|O ,|O a|O decision|O McClellan|I-PER blamed|O for|O the|O ultimate|O failure|O of|O the|O Peninsula|I-MISC Campaign|I-MISC .|O
Pope|O complied|O with|O Lincoln|I-PER 's|O strategic|O desire|O to|O move|O toward|O Richmond|I-LOC from|O the|O north|O ,|O thus|O protecting|O the|O capital|O from|O attack|O .|O
In|O response|O to|O his|O failure|O ,|O Pope|O was|O sent|O to|O Minnesota|I-LOC to|O fight|O the|O Sioux|I-MISC .|O
Burnside|I-PER was|O politically|O neutral|O ,|O which|O Lincoln|I-PER desired|O ,|O and|O for|O the|O most|O part|O supported|O the|O President|O 's|O aims|O .|O
Burnside|I-PER had|O promised|O to|O follow|O through|O on|O Lincoln|I-PER 's|O strategic|O vision|O for|O a|O strong|O offensive|O against|O Lee|I-PER and|O Richmond|I-LOC .|O
After|O Burnside|I-PER was|O stunningly|O defeated|O at|O Fredericksburg|I-LOC in|O December|O ,|O Joseph|I-PER Hooker|I-PER took|O command|O ,|O despite|O his|O history|O of|O "|O loose|O talk|O "|O and|O criticizing|O former|O commanders|O .|O
Hooker|I-PER was|O routed|O by|O Lee|I-PER at|O the|O Battle|I-LOC of|I-LOC Chancellorsville|I-LOC in|O May|O ,|O 1863|O ,|O but|O continued|O to|O command|O his|O troops|O for|O roughly|O two|O months|O .|O
Hooker|I-PER did|O not|O agree|O with|O Lincoln|I-PER 's|O desire|O to|O divide|O his|O troops|O ,|O and|O possibly|O force|O Lee|I-PER to|O do|O the|O same|O ,|O and|O tendered|O his|O resignation|O ,|O which|O was|O accepted|O .|O
During|O the|O Gettysburg|I-MISC Campaign|I-MISC he|O was|O replaced|O by|O George|I-PER Meade|I-PER .|O
In|O a|O letter|O to|O Andrew|I-PER Johnson|I-PER ,|O the|O military|O governor|O of|O Tenn.|I-LOC ,|O encouraging|O him|O to|O lead|O the|O way|O in|O raising|O black|O troops|O ,|O Lincoln|I-PER wrote|O ,|O "|O The|O bare|O sight|O of|O fifty|O thousand|O armed|O ,|O and|O drilled|O black|O soldiers|O on|O the|O banks|O of|O the|O Mississippi|I-LOC would|O end|O the|O rebellion|O at|O once|O .|O "|O
After|O the|O Union|I-LOC victory|I-LOC at|O Gettysburg|I-LOC ,|O Meade|I-PER 's|O failure|O to|O pursue|O Lee|I-PER and|O months|O of|O inactivity|O for|O the|O Army|I-ORG of|I-ORG the|I-ORG Potomac|I-ORG persuaded|O Lincoln|I-PER that|O a|O change|O was|O needed|O .|O
McClellan|I-PER was|O seeking|O the|O Democratic|I-MISC nomination|O for|O President|O ,|O and|O Lincoln|I-PER worried|O that|O Grant|I-PER might|O also|O have|O political|O aspirations|O .|O
Responding|O to|O criticism|O of|O Grant|I-PER after|O the|O 1862|O battle|I-LOC of|I-LOC Shiloh|I-LOC ,|O Lincoln|I-PER reportedly|O had|O said|O ,|O "|O I|O ca|O n't|O spare|O this|O man|O .|O
Grant|I-PER waged|O his|O bloody|O Overland|I-MISC Campaign|I-MISC in|O 1864|O .|O
"|O I|O propose|O to|O fight|O it|O out|O on|O this|O line|O if|O it|O takes|O all|O summer,|O "|O replied|O Grant|I-PER .|O
The|O Confederacy|I-LOC was|O out|O of|O replacements|O ,|O so|O Lee|I-PER 's|O army|O shrank|O with|O every|O battle|O ,|O forcing|O it|O back|O to|O trenches|O outside|O Petersburg|I-MISC .|O
In|O April|O 1865|O ,|O Lee|I-PER 's|O army|O finally|O crumbled|O under|O Grant|I-PER 's|O pounding|O ,|O and|O Richmond|I-LOC fell|O .|O
The|O damage|O caused|O by|O Sherman|I-MISC 's|I-MISC March|I-MISC to|I-MISC the|I-MISC Sea|I-MISC through|O Ga.|I-LOC totaled|O more|O than|O $|O 100|O million|O by|O the|O general|O 's|O own|O estimate|O .|O
Lincoln|I-PER grasped|O the|O need|O to|O control|O strategic|O points|O (|O such|O as|O the|O Mississippi|I-LOC River|I-LOC and|O the|O fortress|O city|O of|O Vicksburg|I-MISC )|O and|O understood|O the|O importance|O of|O defeating|O the|O enemy|O 's|O army|O ,|O rather|O than|O simply|O capturing|O territory|O .|O
He|O had|O ,|O however|O ,|O limited|O success|O in|O motivating|O his|O commanders|O to|O adopt|O his|O strategies|O until|O late|O 1863|O ,|O when|O he|O found|O a|O man|O who|O shared|O his|O vision|O of|O the|O war|O in|O Ulysses|I-PER S.|I-PER Grant|I-PER .|O
Two|O days|O a|O week|O ,|O Lincoln|I-PER would|O meet|O with|O his|O cabinet|O in|O the|O afternoon|O ,|O and|O occasionally|O his|O wife|O would|O force|O him|O to|O take|O a|O carriage|O ride|O because|O she|O was|O concerned|O he|O was|O working|O too|O hard|O .|O
Throughout|O the|O war|O ,|O Lincoln|I-PER showed|O an|O intense|O interest|O in|O the|O military|O campaigns|O .|O
He|O expected|O to|O cause|O the|O eventual|O extinction|O of|O slavery|O by|O stopping|O its|O further|O expansion|O into|O any|O U.S.|I-LOC territory|O ,|O and|O by|O persuading|O states|O to|O accept|O compensated|O emancipation|O if|O the|O state|O would|O outlaw|O slavery|O .|O
In|O it|O ,|O he|O stated|O that|O "|O as|O a|O fit|O and|O necessary|O military|O measure|O "|O on|O January|O 1|O ,|O 1863|O ,|O "|O all|O persons|O held|O as|O a|O slaves|O "|O in|O the|O Confederate|I-LOC states|I-LOC will|O "|O thenceforward|O ,|O and|O forever|O ,|O be|O free|O .|O "|O
Lincoln|I-PER later|O said|O :|O "|O I|O never|O ,|O in|O my|O life|O ,|O felt|O more|O certain|O that|O I|O was|O doing|O right|O ,|O than|O I|O do|O in|O signing|O this|O paper|O .|O "|O
For|O some|O time|O ,|O Lincoln|I-PER continued|O earlier|O plans|O to|O set|O up|O colonies|O for|O the|O newly|O freed|O slaves|O .|O
As|O Frederick|I-PER Douglass|I-PER observed|O ,|O Lincoln|I-PER was|O ,|O "|O The|O first|O great|O man|O that|O I|O talked|O with|O in|O the|O United|I-LOC States|I-LOC freely|O who|O in|O no|O single|O instance|O reminded|O me|O of|O the|O difference|O between|O himself|O and|O myself|O ,|O of|O the|O difference|O of|O color|O .|O "|O
Although|O the|O Battle|I-LOC of|I-LOC Gettysburg|I-LOC was|O a|O Union|I-LOC victory|I-LOC ,|O it|O was|O also|O the|O bloodiest|O battle|O of|O the|O war|O and|O dealt|O a|O blow|O to|O Lincoln|I-PER 's|O war|O effort|O .|O
Lincoln|I-PER 's|O 1863|O military|O drafts|O were|O considered|O "|O odious|O "|O among|O many|O in|O the|O north|O ,|O particularly|O immigrants|O .|O
The|O New|I-MISC York|I-MISC Draft|I-MISC Riots|I-MISC of|O July|O 1863|O were|O the|O most|O notable|O manifestation|O of|O this|O discontent|O .|O
Therefore|O ,|O in|O the|O fall|O of|O 1863|O ,|O Lincoln|I-PER 's|O principal|O aim|O was|O to|O sustain|O public|O support|O for|O the|O war|O effort|O .|O
This|O goal|O became|O the|O focus|O of|O his|O address|O at|O the|O Gettysburg|I-LOC battlefield|O cemetery|O on|O November|O 19|O .|O
The|O Gettysburg|I-PER Address|I-PER is|O one|O of|O the|O most|O quoted|O speeches|O in|O United|I-ORG States|I-ORG history|I-ORG .|O
Abraham|I-PER Lincoln|I-PER 's|O carefully|O crafted|O address|O ,|O secondary|O to|O other|O presentations|O that|O day|O ,|O came|O to|O be|O regarded|O as|O one|O of|O the|O greatest|O speeches|O in|O American|I-ORG history|I-ORG .|O
In|O just|O over|O two|O minutes|O ,|O Lincoln|I-PER invoked|O the|O principles|O of|O human|O equality|O espoused|O by|O the|O Declaration|I-MISC of|I-MISC Independence|I-MISC and|O redefined|O the|O Civil|I-MISC War|I-MISC as|O a|O struggle|O not|O merely|O for|O the|O Union|I-LOC ,|O but|O as|O "|O a|O new|O birth|O of|O freedom|O "|O that|O would|O bring|O true|O equality|O to|O all|O of|O its|O citizens|O ,|O and|O that|O would|O also|O create|O a|O unified|O nation|O in|O which|O states|O '|O rights|O were|O no|O longer|O dominant|O .|O
Nevertheless|O ,|O Republicans|I-MISC across|O the|O country|O feared|O that|O Lincoln|I-PER would|O be|O defeated|O .|O
Lincoln|I-PER did|O not|O show|O the|O pledge|O to|O his|O cabinet|O ,|O but|O asked|O them|O to|O sign|O the|O sealed|O envelope|O .|O
While|O the|O Democratic|I-MISC platform|O followed|O the|O Peace|I-ORG wing|I-ORG of|O the|O party|O and|O called|O the|O war|O a|O "|O failure,|O "|O their|O candidate|O ,|O General|O George|I-PER B.|I-PER McClellan|I-PER ,|O supported|O the|O war|O and|O repudiated|O the|O platform|O .|O
Lincoln|I-PER provided|O Grant|I-PER with|O new|O replacements|O and|O mobilized|O his|O party|O to|O support|O Grant|I-PER and|O win|O local|O support|O for|O the|O war|O effort|O .|O
At|O this|O time|O ,|O a|O victory|O over|O the|O rebels|O was|O at|O hand|O ,|O slavery|O was|O dead|O ,|O and|O Lincoln|I-PER was|O looking|O to|O the|O future|O .|O
Of|O special|O importance|O were|O Tennessee|I-LOC ,|O where|O Lincoln|I-PER appointed|O Andrew|I-PER Johnson|I-PER as|O governor|O ,|O and|O La.|I-LOC ,|O where|O Lincoln|I-PER attempted|O a|O plan|O that|O would|O restore|O statehood|O when|O 10|O %|O of|O the|O voters|O agreed|O to|O it|O .|O
This|O allowed|O the|O president|O to|O confer|O in|O person|O with|O Grant|I-PER and|O Sherman|I-PER about|O ending|O hostilities|O (|O as|O Sherman|I-PER coincidentally|O managed|O a|O hasty|O visit|O to|O Grant|I-PER from|O his|O forces|O in|O North|I-LOC Carolina|I-LOC at|O the|O same|O time|O )|O .|O
He|O was|O greeted|O at|O the|O city|O as|O a|O conquering|O hero|O by|O freed|O slaves|O ,|O whose|O sentiments|O were|O epitomized|O by|O one|O admirer|O 's|O quote|O ,|O "|O I|O know|O I|O am|O free|O for|O I|O have|O seen|O the|O face|O of|O Father|O Abraham|I-PER and|O have|O felt|O him|O .|O "|O
Lincoln|I-PER 's|O rhetoric|O defined|O the|O issues|O of|O the|O war|O for|O the|O nation|O ,|O the|O world|O ,|O and|O posterity|O .|O
The|O Gettysburg|I-PER Address|I-PER defied|O Lincoln|I-PER 's|O own|O prediction|O that|O "|O the|O world|O will|O little|O note|O ,|O nor|O long|O remember|O what|O we|O say|O here|O .|O "|O
In|O recent|O years|O ,|O historians|O have|O stressed|O Lincoln|I-PER 's|O use|O of|O and|O redefinition|O of|O republican|O values|O .|O
Nevertheless|O ,|O in|O 1861|O Lincoln|I-PER justified|O the|O war|O in|O terms|O of|O legalisms|O ,|O and|O then|O in|O terms|O of|O the|O national|O duty|O to|O guarantee|O a|O "|O republican|O form|O of|O government|O "|O in|O every|O state|O .|O
While|O some|O critics|O say|O Lincoln|I-PER moved|O too|O far|O and|O too|O fast|O ,|O they|O agree|O that|O he|O dedicated|O the|O nation|O to|O values|O that|O marked|O "|O a|O new|O founding|O of|O the|O nation|O .|O "|O
In|O 1861|O ,|O Lincoln|I-PER signed|O the|O second|O and|O third|O Morrill|I-ORG Tariff|I-ORG (|O the|O first|O had|O become|O law|O under|O James|I-PER Buchanan|I-PER )|O .|O
Lincoln|I-PER also|O presided|O over|O the|O expansion|O of|O the|O federal|O government|O 's|O economic|O influence|O in|O several|O other|O areas|O .|O
The|O creation|O of|O the|O system|O of|O national|O banks|O by|O the|O National|I-ORG Banking|I-ORG Acts|I-ORG of|O 1863|O ,|O 1864|O ,|O and|O 1865|O allowed|O the|O creation|O of|O a|O strong|O national|O financial|O system|O .|O
The|O last|O such|O proclamation|O was|O during|O James|I-PER Madison|I-PER 's|O presidency|O fifty|O years|O before|O .|O
After|O attending|O an|O April|O 11|O speech|O in|O which|O Lincoln|I-PER promoted|O voting|O rights|O for|O blacks|O ,|O an|O incensed|O Booth|I-PER changed|O his|O plans|O and|O determined|O to|O assassinate|O the|O president|O .|O
Learning|O that|O the|O President|O and|O First|O Lady|O would|O be|O attending|O Ford|I-LOC 's|I-LOC Theatre|I-LOC ,|O he|O laid|O his|O plans|O ,|O assigning|O his|O co-conspirators|O to|O assassinate|O Vice|O President|O Andrew|I-PER Johnson|I-PER and|O Secretary|O of|O State|O William|I-PER H.|I-PER Seward|I-PER .|O
Without|O his|O main|O bodyguard|O Ward|I-PER Hill|I-PER Lamon|I-PER ,|O to|O whom|O he|O related|O his|O famous|O dream|O regarding|O his|O own|O assassination|O ,|O Lincoln|I-PER left|O to|O attend|O the|O play|O Our|I-MISC American|I-MISC Cousin|I-MISC on|O April|O 14|O ,|O 1865|O .|O
As|O a|O lone|O bodyguard|O wandered|O ,|O and|O Lincoln|I-PER sat|O in|O his|O state|O box|O in|O the|O balcony|O ,|O Booth|I-PER crept|O up|O behind|O the|O President|O and|O waited|O for|O what|O he|O thought|O would|O be|O the|O funniest|O line|O of|O the|O play|O (|O "|O You|O sock-dologizing|O old|O man-trap|O "|O )|O ,|O hoping|O the|O laughter|O would|O muffle|O the|O noise|O of|O the|O gunshot|O .|O
When|O the|O laughter|O began|O ,|O Booth|I-PER jumped|O into|O the|O box|O and|O aimed|O a|O single-shot|O ,|O round-ball|O .44|O caliber|O (|O 11|O mm|O )|O Deringer|I-PER at|O his|O head|O ,|O firing|O at|O point-blank|O range|O .|O
Major|O Henry|I-PER Rathbone|I-PER momentarily|O grappled|O with|O Booth|I-PER but|O was|O cut|O by|O Booth|I-PER 's|O knife|O .|O
Booth|I-PER then|O leaped|O to|O the|O stage|O and|O shouted|O "|O Sic|I-PER semper|I-PER tyrannis|I-PER !|O "|O
(|O Latin|I-MISC :|O Thus|I-PER always|I-PER to|I-PER tyrants|I-PER )|O and|O escaped|O ,|O despite|O suffering|O a|O broken|O leg|O in|O the|O leap|O .|O
He|O was|O eventually|O cornered|O in|O a|O Va.|I-LOC barn|O house|O and|O shot|O ,|O dying|O of|O his|O wounds|O soon|O after|O .|O
The|O President|O was|O taken|O across|O the|O street|O from|O the|O theater|O to|O the|O Petersen|I-LOC House|I-LOC ,|O where|O he|O lay|O in|O a|O coma|O for|O nine|O hours|O before|O dying|O .|O
Several|O physicians|O attended|O Lincoln|I-PER ,|O including|O U.S.|I-ORG Army|I-ORG Surgeon|I-ORG General|I-ORG Joseph|I-PER K.|I-PER Barnes|I-PER of|O the|O Army|I-ORG Medical|I-ORG Museum|I-ORG .|O
Lincoln|I-PER never|O regained|O consciousness|O and|O was|O pronounced|O dead|O at|O 7:22:10|O a.m.|O April|O 15|O ,|O 1865|O .|O
Lincoln|I-PER 's|O body|O was|O carried|O by|O train|O in|O a|O grand|O funeral|O procession|O through|O several|O states|O on|O its|O way|O back|O to|O Illinois|I-LOC .|O
While|O much|O of|O the|O nation|O mourned|O him|O as|O the|O savior|O of|I-LOC the|I-LOC United|I-LOC States|I-LOC ,|O Copperheads|I-ORG celebrated|O the|O death|O of|O a|O man|O they|O considered|O a|O tyrant|O .|O
The|O Lincoln|I-LOC Tomb|I-LOC in|O Oak|I-LOC Ridge|I-LOC Cemetery|I-LOC in|O Springfield|I-LOC ,|O Illinois|I-LOC ,|O is|O 177|O feet|O (|O 54|O m|O )|O tall|O and|O ,|O by|O 1874|O ,|O was|O surmounted|O with|O several|O bronze|O statues|O of|O Lincoln|I-PER .|O
To|O prevent|O repeated|O attempts|O to|O steal|O Lincoln|I-PER 's|O body|O and|O hold|O it|O for|O ransom|O ,|O Robert|I-PER Todd|I-PER Lincoln|I-PER had|O it|O exhumed|O and|O reinterred|O in|O concrete|O several|O feet|O thick|O in|O 1901|O .|O
In|O March|O 1860|O in|O a|O speech|O in|O New|I-LOC Haven|I-LOC ,|O Connecticut|I-ORG ,|O Lincoln|I-PER said|O ,|O regarding|O slavery|O ,|O "|O Whenever|O this|O question|O shall|O be|O settled|O ,|O it|O must|O be|O settled|O on|O some|O philosophical|O basis|O .|O
The|O philosophical|O basis|O for|O Lincoln|I-PER 's|O beliefs|O regarding|O slavery|O and|O other|O issues|O of|O the|O day|O require|O that|O Lincoln|I-PER be|O examined|O "|O seriously|O as|O a|O man|O of|O ideas|O .|O "|O
Lincoln|I-PER was|O a|O strong|O supporter|O of|O the|O American|I-MISC Whig|I-ORG version|O of|O liberal|O capitalism|O .|O
There|O were|O few|O people|O who|O strongly|O or|O directly|O influenced|O Lincoln|I-PER 's|O moral|O and|O intellectual|O development|O and|O perspectives|O .|O
There|O was|O no|O teacher|O ,|O mentor|O ,|O church|O leader|O ,|O community|O leader|O ,|O or|O peer|O that|O Lincoln|I-PER would|O credit|O in|O later|O years|O as|O a|O strong|O influence|O on|O his|O intellectual|O development|O .|O
Lacking|O a|O formal|O education|O ,|O Lincoln|I-PER 's|O personal|O philosophy|O was|O shaped|O by|O "|O an|O amazingly|O retentive|O memory|O and|O a|O passion|O for|O reading|O and|O learning|O .|O "|O
It|O was|O Lincoln|I-PER 's|O reading|O ,|O rather|O than|O his|O relationships|O ,|O that|O were|O most|O influential|O in|O shaping|O his|O personal|O beliefs|O .|O
In|O 1846|O Lincoln|I-PER described|O the|O effect|O of|O this|O doctrine|O as|O "|O that|O the|O human|O mind|O is|O impelled|O to|O action|O ,|O or|O held|O in|O rest|O by|O some|O power|O ,|O over|O which|O the|O mind|O itself|O has|O no|O control|O .|O "|O
As|O Lincoln|I-PER matured|O ,|O and|O especially|O during|O his|O term|O as|O president|O ,|O the|O idea|O of|O a|O divine|O will|O somehow|O interacting|O with|O human|O affairs|O increasingly|O influenced|O his|O public|O expressions|O .|O
On|O a|O personal|O level|O ,|O the|O death|O of|O his|O son|O Willie|I-PER in|O February|O 1862|O may|O have|O caused|O Lincoln|I-PER to|O look|O towards|O religion|O for|O answers|O and|O solace|O .|O
Consistent|O with|O the|O common|O practice|O of|O the|O Whig|I-ORG party|O ,|O Lincoln|I-PER would|O often|O use|O the|O Declaration|I-MISC of|I-MISC Independence|I-MISC as|O the|O philosophical|O and|O moral|O expression|O of|O these|O two|O philosophies|O .|O
In|O claiming|O that|O all|O men|O were|O created|O free|O ,|O Lincoln|I-PER and|O the|O Whigs|I-ORG argued|O that|O this|O freedom|O required|O economic|O advancement|O ,|O expanded|O education|O ,|O territory|O to|O grow|O ,|O and|O the|O ability|O of|O the|O nation|O to|O absorb|O the|O growing|O immigrant|O population|O .|O
He|O saw|O the|O Declaration|I-MISC as|O more|O than|O a|O political|O document|O .|O
Among|O contemporary|O admirers|O ,|O Lincoln|I-PER is|O usually|O seen|O as|O personifying|O classical|O values|O of|O honesty|O and|O integrity|O ,|O as|O well|O as|O respect|O for|O individual|O and|O minority|O rights|O ,|O and|O human|O freedom|O in|O general|O .|O
The|O Lincoln|I-ORG automobile|I-ORG brand|I-ORG is|O also|O named|O after|O him|O .|O
The|O ballistic|O missile|O submarine|O Abraham|I-MISC Lincoln|I-MISC (|O SSBN-602|I-MISC )|O and|O the|O aircraft|O carrier|O Abraham|I-MISC Lincoln|I-MISC (|O CVN-72|I-MISC )|O were|O named|O in|O his|O honor|O .|O
During|O the|O Spanish|I-MISC Civil|I-MISC War|I-MISC ,|O the|O American|I-MISC faction|O of|O the|O International|I-ORG Brigades|I-ORG named|O themselves|O the|O Abraham|I-ORG Lincoln|I-ORG Brigade|I-ORG .|O
